<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>The scourge of securitie, or The expulsion and returne of the vncleane spirit. By William Est, minister and preacher of Gods word, at Bedford in Deuonshire</title>
            <author>Est, William, 1546 or 7-1625.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1609</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 119 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 56 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2014-11">2014-11 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A00407</idno>
            <idno type="STC">STC 10537</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC S111377</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99846739</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99846739</idno>
            <idno type="VID">11726</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online text creation partnership.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A00407)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 11726)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1475-1640 ; 1236:3)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>The scourge of securitie, or The expulsion and returne of the vncleane spirit. By William Est, minister and preacher of Gods word, at Bedford in Deuonshire</title>
                  <author>Est, William, 1546 or 7-1625.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[8], 47, 32-48, 65-82 [i.e. 100], [2] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed by T[homas] C[reede] for Thomas Downe, and Ephraim Dauson, and are to be solde at their shop in Fleete-streete, at the Inner Temple-gate,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1609.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>A commentary on Luke I, 14-27.</note>
                  <note>Printer's name from STC.</note>
                  <note>Cf. Folger catalogue, which give signatures: A⁴ B-G H⁴ (-H3).</note>
                  <note>P. 100 misnumbered 82.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the Princeton Theological Seminary. Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Bible. --  N.T. --  Luke I, 14-27 --  Commentaries --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Christian life --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2013-10</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-10</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-11</date>
            <label>Olivia Bottum</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-11</date>
            <label>Olivia Bottum</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2014-03</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:11726:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>THE SCOVRGE of Securitie, OR THE EXPVLSION and returne of the vncleane Spirit.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>By</hi> William Eſt, <hi>Miniſter and Preacher of Gods word, at Bedford in Deuonſhire.</hi>
            </p>
            <q>
               <bibl>2. <hi>Pet.</hi> 2.<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>0.</bibl>
               <p>For if they, after they haue eſcaped from the fil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thineſſe of the world through the knowiedge of the Lord, and of the Sauiour Ieſus Chriſt, are yet tangled againe therein, and ouercome, the laſt end is worſe with them then the be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ginning.</p>
            </q>
            <p>LONDON, Printed by <hi>T. C.</hi> for <hi>Thomas Downe,</hi> and <hi>Ephraim Dauſon,</hi> and are to be ſolde at their Shop in Fleete-ſtreete, at the Inner Tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple-gate. 1609.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="dedication">
            <pb facs="tcp:11726:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:11726:2"/>
            <head>TO THE RIGHT Worſhipfull <hi>S. Barnard Grayn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ile</hi> Knight, my ſingular good Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tron: all increaſe of ſpirituall bleſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſings in this life, and <hi>euer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>laſting bleſſedneſſe in the life to come.</hi>
            </head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">H</seg>Auing (Right Wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhipfull) rudely caſt the plot of this pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent pamphlet, for mine owne priuate vſe and meditation, and for the better edifying of the flocke committed vnto my charge, (as it may appeare by the <hi>tenue fi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lum,</hi> incompt and vnpoliſhed parts of this edifice) it chanced to come into the hands of ſome of my fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miliar
<pb facs="tcp:11726:3"/>and aſſured friends, which when they had peruſed it, laboured to perſwade me to permit to paſſe into the publicke viewe of the world, laying before me the profit which of this ſubiect, many (eſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cially in theſe ſinfull times) might reape. But (to ſpeake the truth) <hi>ſuadebant potius quam perſuadebant,</hi> they motioned rather then moued me, as vtterly vnwilling to peſter the print, or oppreſſe the preſſe with more pamphlets which ſee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>meth to grone alreadie vnder ſuch burthens, and chiefely in this cu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rious criticall and carping age; al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wayes hating that humour which the <hi>Eatyriſt Iuuenal,</hi> noted in this dayes: <hi>Tenet inſanabile multos Scri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bend, cacoethes.</hi> Beſide, when I ſaw many well furniſhed, rich men to caſt of their ſuperfluitie in the Lords treaſure, I iudged my poore Widowes mite to be needeleſſe.
<pb facs="tcp:11726:3"/>Yet at length being ouercome with their importunities, and ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uing euer a deſire to doe good, and that by all meanes (which more preuailed with me then any thing elſe,) I yeelded to their requeſts, and ſuffered it to paſſe as it is, vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poliſhed, hauing no leiſure by rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon of my other imployments, to adorne it with any other coate, then the firſt. And reſolued with my ſelfe, that if among ſo many maiſter builders, I do but as a poore labourer bring ſtones, or morter, or the leaſt thing towards the building of the temple, it may ſtand in ſome ſteede. For though this age be furniſhed, with many excel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lent writers; <hi>ad nauſeam vſque,</hi> yet of ſuch as labour to make the Theo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ricke of Chriſtianitie, meete with the practicke, the preſſe (I thinke) doth not ſurfet. As for the viperous teeth of baſe <hi>Momus</hi> his mates, to
<pb facs="tcp:11726:4"/>whome it is eaſier <hi>momeiſthai potiut quam mimeiſthai,</hi> to emulate rather then imitate the good purpoſe of others, let them know I litle regard their <hi>Theonine</hi> barkings. Only this with <hi>Martial</hi> I tell them, <hi>Carpere vel noli noſtra, velede tua:</hi>
               <q>
                  <l>Either ceaſe to carpe at writing mine,</l>
                  <l>Or elſe ſet forth ſome thing of thine.</l>
               </q>
            </p>
            <p>But the courteous reader I re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>queſt to iudge freely, admoniſh friendly, and correct charitablie. And I in the meane time <hi>ſub tabulit deliteſcam,</hi> imitating that excellent painter <hi>Apelles,</hi> and will hearken vnto his friendly cenſure. This ſmall paper gift I commende vnto your Worſhips protection, being the beſt at this time that I am able to giue, deſiring your fauourable acceptance of this pledge of my good will, which if it be worthy a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nie
<pb facs="tcp:11726:4"/>reſpect, to you being my Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tron in many reſpects it is due. And thus with the penner of the ſtorie of the <hi>Machabees</hi> I end: If I haue done well, and as my text required, let God haue the glorie, but if I haue done ſlenderly and barely, it is that I could. I beſeech the Al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mighty to bleſſe, preſerue, &amp; keepe you and yours, and to powre his ſpiritual graces vpon you in this life preſent, &amp; bring you to the fruitio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of his euerlaſting glory in the life to come. From <hi>Bydforde.</hi> Ianuary. 6. 1609.</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>
                  <hi>Your Worſhips in Chriſt to command,</hi> William Eſte.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb facs="tcp:11726:5"/>
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:11726:5"/>
            <head>THE SCOVRGE OF Securitie.</head>
            <epigraph>
               <q>
                  <bibl>
                     <hi>Luc. 11.14. vnto verſe 17.</hi>
                  </bibl>
                  <p>Then he caſt out a Diuel, &amp;c.</p>
               </q>
            </epigraph>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>His Scripture (dearely beloued) offereth vnto vs this generall diuiſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on.</p>
            <p n="1">1 The myracle it ſelfe, of the Diuell caſt out of the man that was dumbe, <hi>verſe</hi> 14.</p>
            <p n="2">2 The diuers iudgments of the be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>holders concerning the ſame, <hi>verſe</hi> 15.16.</p>
            <p n="3">3 The Apologie of <hi>Christ</hi> againſt the calumniation of the <hi>Phariſies</hi> and Iewes: from <hi>ver.</hi> 17. vnto 27.</p>
            <p n="1">
               <pb n="2" facs="tcp:11726:6"/> 1 The myracle it ſelfe, the Euange<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liſt deſcribeth in fewe words, 1. <hi>Sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iectum in quo editum,</hi> when hee ſaith, which was <hi>dumbe: per metonymians effecti.</hi> becauſe he made the <hi>man dumbe</hi> whom he poſſeſſed. Miſerable therefore was the condition of this wretched man, which is heere amplified <hi>a priuantibus,</hi> for he was not only <hi>dumbe,</hi> but alſo <hi>deafe, Mar.</hi> 7. For the Greeke <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> ſignifieth both <hi>deafe</hi> &amp; <hi>dumbe:</hi> becauſe for the moſt part the <hi>dumbe</hi> are alſo <hi>deafe,</hi> for (after the opinion of the Phi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſitions) by reaſon of the mutuall co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſent of the muſcles and nerues which ſerue both the tongue and hearing, <hi>vno vitia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to alterum laedi ſolet. Mat.</hi> 12.22. ſaith, <hi>he was alſo blind.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="2">2 The forme alſo of the myracle is expreſſed, when it is ſayd, that the Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uell was caſt out by the omnipotent power of God, and the man deliuered from his crueltie.</p>
            <p n="3">3 For the illuſtration of the myra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cle, he amplifieth the ſame, <hi>ab effectis contrariis,</hi> when hee addeth, that the Diuell being caſt out, <hi>the dumbe ſpake:</hi> 
               <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> 
               <hi>qui ante fuerit mu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tus,</hi>
               <pb n="3" facs="tcp:11726:6"/>and the <hi>deafe did heare,</hi> and the <hi>blind ſaw. Mas.</hi> 12.22.</p>
            <div type="part">
               <head>Obſer. &amp; doctri.</head>
               <p n="1">1 THis fearefull ſpectacles of the poſſeſſed, ſetteth before our eies the great malice and power of Sathan, which by Gods permiſſion inuadeth the liuing bodies of men, mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerably afflicted, horriblie tormen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teth, and deformeth them: as it appea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teth in the poſſeſſed with a dumbe <hi>ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rite, Mar.</hi> 9. in the lunaticke, <hi>Mat.</hi> 17. in the poſſeſſed with a legion of Diuels moſt cruellie, <hi>Luc.</hi> 8. and diuers other, he goeth about like a roaring Lyon, 1. <hi>Pet.</hi> 5. as a hunter to lay ſnares, <hi>Pſ.</hi> 91.3. as a Fowler to ſpred his net, and ſnares to catch ſoules, <hi>Pſ.</hi> 124. deſiring to winnow vs as wheate, <hi>Luc.</hi> 22. and la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>boureth to draw vs to horrible ſinne and wickedneſſe, hauing great wrath. <hi>Apoc.</hi> 12. Infomuch, <hi>Vt ſi tantum nocere poſſet quantum vellet, aliquis iuſtorum non remaneret. Aug.</hi> Wee are here to note, that the Diuel tormented this man but
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:11726:7"/>by the permiſſion of God, for he could not enter into the heard of Swine without the leaue of Chriſt. <hi>Mat.</hi> 8. Therefore it is ſaid. 1. <hi>Sam.</hi> 16. <hi>that the</hi> euill ſpirit of God came vpon <hi>Saul,</hi> be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe he is the creature of God, and his miniſter, ſo that without the licence of God, hee cannot ſo much as ſhake one leafe from a tree. And this permiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion God giueth him, both in the god<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, and in the wicked, as it appeareth in <hi>Iob.</hi> 2. Hee many times afflicteth them both, but for diuers reſpects and ends: the wicked for their puniſhme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t &amp; cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rection; the godly for their triall, good and increaſe of their glorie. Here learn, that for many cauſes God permitteth the Diuell to poſſeſſe and afflict men in this life.</p>
               <p n="1">1 That hauing before our eyes how tyrannouſly and cruelly hee dealeth with vs, we ſhould proſecute him with extreame hatred, hold euer enmitie with him, much leſſe to hearken to his counſailes and ſuggeſtions, and by theſe externall perſecutions, to conſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der how much more grieuouſly he de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſireth
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:11726:7"/>to afflict the ſoule: and for this cauſe God permitteth him to appeare ſometime in horrible and vgly ſhapes, that we ſhould deteſt and flie from him as from a moſt pernicious peſtilence.</p>
               <p n="2">2 That ſetting before our eies the crueltie of this infernall <hi>Leuiathan,</hi> we ſhould be ſober and <hi>watch,</hi> 1. <hi>Pet.</hi> 5. and at euerie moment commende our ſelues to God, and whether we riſe or lie downe, to pray vnto God for his de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fence and protection, and ſay with <hi>Chryſoſtome, Renuncio tibi diabole; et do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>me tibi Christe.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="3">3 That with the ſwiniſh Epicures, we ſhould not thinke theſe things to be <hi>inania terriculamenta,</hi> nor at euerie three words, and light occaſion (as the manner of ſome prophane perſons is) to imprecate, curſe, or deuote our ſelues or others to the Diuell. Which ſurely is a thing ſo much the more greatly to be lamented, as we ſee it common in the world, that ſeeing the Diuell is ſuch an enemie vnto man, any ſhould haue his odious &amp; deteſtable name euer in their mouths, yea the verie infants following
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:11726:8"/>the wicked example of their elders, e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen from their cradles, in curſing and banning (reiecting the ſweete name of Ieſus) toſſe too &amp; fro this odious name in their mouthes.</p>
               <p n="4">4 That as often as we behold any poſſeſſed, deafe, dumbe, that we ſhould call to minde the filthineſſe of ſinne, which is cauſe that ſuch power is giuen vnto the Diuell vpon men; and learne to deteſt ſinne, <hi>quae vita ſunt diaboli, Ori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gin.</hi> For as long as ſinne raigneth in a man, <hi>tamdiu victus a diabolo poſſidetur, &amp; vexatur. Aug.</hi> To conclude this; when we haue a ſound and perfect bodie, let vs giue God thankes, and vſe the vigor both of minde and members, godly, to his praiſe and glorie.</p>
               <p n="2">2 The corporall poſſeſſion of the Diuell in this wretched man, putteth vs in minde of the ſpirituall poſſeſſion of heart, which this enemie of man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kind effecteth in the hearts of them, through his fraude and deceits: for he made this wretched man, not onely <hi>dumbe,</hi> but alſo blind and deafe: that is, depriued him almoſt of all his ſenſes;
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:11726:8"/>all which hee ſpiritually effecteth, in thoſe whom through ſinne he holdeth captiue. For as the ſpirit of God where it reſteth, maketh men dumbe, deafe, and blinde, to earthly and carnall things, that they may giue themſelues to the contemplation of the things a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>boue: ſo this wicked ſpirit laboureth to make them dumbe, deafe, &amp; blinde, to all ſpirituall things, that without all feare of God, and remorſe of conſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence, they might wholy giue them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelues to all filthineſſe. Firſt, euen as the Wolfe when he prayeth vpon the Sheepe, catcheth him firſt by the throate, that he might not crie, leaſt the Shepheard being awaked, ſhould reskue the poore Sheepe from his iawes: ſo this helliſh infernall Wolfe, maketh many mute, that they neuer call vpon God, pray, or euer haue in their mouthes, any godly and ſpirituall co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>munication, which if they knowe or heare any infirmitie by their neigh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bour, forget this rule of Chriſt. <hi>Mat.</hi> 18. <hi>If thy brother treſpaſſe, &amp;c.</hi> And that of the Apoſtles, <hi>Gal.</hi> 6. <hi>Brethren, if a man
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:11726:9"/>be fallen, &amp;c.</hi> But are talkatiue enough, to publiſh it to the infamie and hurt of their brother: ſuch are all vniuſt aduo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cates, which are mute in the poore ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s cauſe, but in the cauſe of the rich, &amp;c. Such are all periured falſe witneſſe-bea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rers, which conceale the truth for a re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward, &amp;c. Another ſort there are, whom the Diuell maketh dumbe, like ſuch as are naturally borne dumbe: for as thoſe that are borne blinde, doe make ſhewe and ſignes, for what they would haue: ſo all hypocrites ſeeke for the glorie &amp; praiſe of men, onely by the outward ſhewes of vertues, they come to Church, ſhewe themſelues zealous, &amp;c. All but only in ſhewe, all but in ſignes; but if thou put them to the touchſtone of Chriſtianitie, <hi>ſhewe me thy faith by thy workes, Iac.</hi> 2. Thou ſhalt find all to bee but in dumbe ſhewes and ſignes, all counterfeit copper and droſſe: looke into their workes, and there you find a worme-eaten conſcience, with the canker of vſurie, the viper of enuie, with the ſerpents of detraction, back biting, &amp;c. Crocadils in diſſimulation, 2. Lyons
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:11726:9"/>in their furie, worſe then the verie Ty<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gers in reuenge, in ſecreate ſtinging likes ſcorpions, &amp;c. All theſe the diuell maketh mute, &amp;c.</p>
               <p n="2">2 The Diuell alſo maketh them whom he ſpiritually poſſeſſeth, blind, that they may not ſee their ſinne, and the daunger they are in; like the Wolfe, he taketh him by the throate, that hee may not call vnto the true Sheapheard <hi>Ieſus Chriſt</hi> for ſuccour, and as a raue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nous Vultur, he ſeeketh to picke out his ſpirituall eies, that the ſinner may not ſee the filthineſſe of ſinne, nor the imminent daunger he is in. The coue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nant which this enemie requireth of his ſeruants, is like that which proude and cruell <hi>Nahaſh</hi> the Ammonite, de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manded of the <hi>Gileadite,</hi> 1. <hi>Sam.</hi> 11. <hi>that he might pull out all their right eies.</hi> In like manner the Diuell ſeeketh to pull out the eies of our minde, that the ſinner ſeeing, might not ſee, <hi>for their owne wickedneſſe hath blinded them. Wiſ.</hi> 2. The ſinfull man and woman, when they are moſt blinded in their wicked<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe, they thinke that they haue <hi>Lyn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceos,
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:11726:10"/>oculos.</hi> Like the foole <hi>Harpaſtes,</hi> that <hi>Sen.</hi> 6. <hi>lib. Epist.</hi> 52. ſpeaketh of, who being ſuddainly depriued of her ſight, <hi>neſcet ſe eſſe caecam, paedagogum rogat vt migret, domum tenebroſam eſſe.</hi> This which we laugh at in her (ſaith hee) we practiſe in our ſelues: <hi>nemo ſe auarum eſſe intelligit, ne cupidum,</hi> yet worſe then the blind in this; they ſeeke a guide, <hi>nos ſine duce erramus, et dicimus, non ego ambitioſus ſum,</hi> I am not couetous, nor luxurious, &amp;c. It is not my vice that I am raſh, angrie, it is the fault of my youth: and therefore we are hardly cured, <hi>quia nos aegrotare neſcimus, nec me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dicum quidem quaerimus:</hi> ſhould we not thinke him to be mad or blind, who being intent in doing ſome thing, one ſhould runne vnto him with a naked ſword, and minace him death, if hee preſently left not off; and notwithſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding without any feare hee goeth on with his worke? would we not thinke him to be blinde, which feeth not the ſword drawne to ſtrike him? And what is the cauſe (I pray you) that ſome men giue themſelues ouer vnto ſo many
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:11726:10"/>ſinnes, and ſecurely wallow in their fil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thineſſe, and ſome others liue ſoberly, warily, and laboureth to auoide euen the ſmalleſt ſinne? Surely the reaſon is, becauſe the one hath the ſpirituall eies of his minde blinded ſo, that hee ſeeth not how great and greeuous euill hang ouer his head, which that high iudge reſerueth for him againſt the day of vengeance: the other ſetting Gods iuſtice before their eyes, and the ſeueritie of the eternall torments, which the iuſt iudge inflicteth vpon theſe ſhort &amp; fading pleaſures of ſinne, by all meanes endeuoureth to refraine the ſame. O that men were not diſtitute of theſe eies of their minde, that they might contemplate vpon the miſeries and torments which are layd vp in hell for the wicked, that they might betime betake them to newneſſe of life, and come out of the ſnares, wherewith this prince of darkneſſe holdeth them cap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiue; and will in the end (vnleſſe they repent) caſt the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> for euer into <hi>vtter dark<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe, where ſhall be weeping and gnaſhing of teeth.</hi> The Diuell now ſtoppeth their
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:11726:11"/>eies with earth, that is, with the vile cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ruptible, &amp; abiect things of the world, for the loue whereof they make ſmall reckoning of the life to come: but then to their perpetuall griefe, they ſhall perceiue how they were blinded, and confeſſe too late, <hi>we haue erred from the way of truth, and the light of righteouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe hath not ſhined vnto vs, Wiſ.</hi> 5.</p>
               <p>Now let vs ſee how the Diuell ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>keth the ſinner alſo deafe: whe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ye ſee a man warned, counſelled, exhorted, per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwaded by many that he ſhould in his iourney turne, and decline from ſuch a way, for ther are theeues lying in wait to take away his money and life: hee harkeneth to none of them, goeth boldly on his iourney, the way infeſted with Theeues, falleth into their hands, is robbed and ſlaine, would yee not think this man to be deaf, or out of his wits? In like manner when God by his word, Preachers, diuine inſpirations, &amp;c. Inceſſantly warneth, and calleth vnto the ſinner, knocketh at <hi>the doore of their hearts, deſireth, craueth, and beg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>geth them to open vnto him, his head being
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:11726:11"/>full of deawe, and his locke of the droppes of the night. Cant.</hi> 5.2. Sheweth him the dangerous courſe he taketh, the pit of deſtruction he is falling into, the way he goeth leadeth to eternall torments, &amp;c. Notwithſtanding, hee will not heare, but goeth on ſtill the broade way that leadeth vnto hell: ſhall we doubt but that the Diuell hath ſtopped the ſpirituall eares of ſuch?</p>
               <p>Thus yee ſee how the Diuell maketh the ſinner dumbe, deafe, and blind, that he may the more quietly keepe poſſeſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion of his ſoule. Euen as a man that would quietly ſleepe and take his reſt, commandeth his ſeruants and familie to keepe ſilence, that the noiſe may not diſturbe him: 2. hee ſhutteth the win<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dowes that the light may not offend his eies, hee getteth him into a cloſe roome, and if any enquire for him, wil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leth his ſeruants to denie him to bee within: all theſe this ſubtile enemie of mankind cauſeth in the ſinner, that he may ſleepe quietly in his ſinne, he dili<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gently laboureth to ſtop the entrings and paſſages of the ſoule, which are the
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:11726:12"/>ſenſes, that no Diuine light ſhould come in at the windowes thereof; to diſperce the darkneſſe, and blindneſſe of the minde: as we ſee in <hi>Pharao,</hi> and the Scribes and Phariſies, which could not bee wonne nor reclaimed by the myracles they ſawe with their cies. And if we beate their eares with neuer ſo many Sermons, lay before their cyes, the ioyes of the heauenly king<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome, the moſt horrible torments of hell, they ſtill perſiſt in their life as if they heard nothing at all: ſo we ſee many to continue ſo indurate, in inue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terate hatred, or in vnchaſt loue, that with no perſwaſions, no preaching, no counſell, they will be reclaimed from their hatred or filthy luſt: who ſeeth not heere the power of the Diuell in ſtopping both their ſpirituall cares and eies, leaſt they ſhould conuert and eſcape out of his clawes? He ſtoppeth alſo their mouths that no ſpirituall co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>munication of God, or godlineſſe, ſhould proceede from thence, partai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning to the ſaluation of their ſoule, when to ſcurrilitie, curſing, &amp;c. and all
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:11726:12"/>corrupt, and rotten communication, their mouthes are alwaies open and la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uiſh. If a man ſhould aske them whoſe mouth ouerrunne with filthy words (like an vncleane Mill that cannot grinde without fowle water) whether they haue had at any time al this yeare, any godly conference concerning God &amp; the ſaluatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of their ſoules: they will anſwere (if they would confeſſe the truth) that they neuer had any thought or ſpeech of any ſuch thing: who doth not heere plainly ſee, that thoſe are al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſo dumbe, though otherwiſe verie tal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>katiue? <hi>vae tacentibus de te domine:</hi> (ſaith <hi>Augustine) quia ipſi loquaces muti ſunt cum non tuas laudes dicunt. Aug. in medit.</hi> And laſtly, he laboreth to keepe the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> conuerſing with good men, leaſt that the light of their good exa<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ples ſhould expell the darkneſſe of their mindes, their wholſome exhortations rouſe the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> from the ſleepe of ſinne, and ſo they might repent &amp; bee turned vnto God, &amp;c. Take heede therefore (ſaith <hi>Cypri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>an) quiſathanam habent ſuggeſtorem, ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bebunt etiam tortorem. In ſer. de ieiuni.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="3">
                  <pb n="16" facs="tcp:11726:13"/> 3 In this one man 4 myracles, were wrought: the deafe did heare, the dumbe ſpake, the blind ſawe, and the poſſeſſed was deliuered. This euident<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly euinceth that Chriſt is the true <hi>Meſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſias,</hi> to ſaue and free vs from the power of Sathan; <hi>who went about doing good, and healing all that were oppreſſed of the Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uell, Act.</hi> 10. <hi>For this purpoſe appeared the Sonne of God, that he might looſe the works of the Diuell.</hi> 1. <hi>Iob.</hi> 3. Let vs therefore flie vnto him in all our dangers and ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſities, and he will <hi>refreſh vs. Mat.</hi> 11.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Finis</hi> 1. <hi>part. vel conc. primae.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>Pars <hi>2.</hi> vel conc. ſecunda.</head>
               <p>IN this part is deſcribed the effect of the myracle, which according to the diuerſitie of the ſubiects was three<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>folde, and that according to the three diuers opinions and iudgement of the beholders.</p>
               <p n="1">1 In the promiſcuall companie ſaith <hi>Mat.</hi> 12.23. <hi>All the people were amazed:</hi> that is, they admired the power of God, which ſhined forth in this myracle, 72.
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:11726:13"/>they ſpake honorably of Chriſt the <hi>Meſſias,</hi> the Author thereof: <hi>Is not this the ſonne of Dauid?</hi> that is, the promiſed ſauiour of the line of <hi>Dauid,</hi> of whom it was foretolde that he ſhould doe ſuch myracles. <hi>Eſa.</hi> 35.5. And this effect of the myracle it ſelfe was good, ſim<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple, true, and ſincere. 2. <hi>verſe</hi> 15. in the <hi>Phariſies,</hi> which maliciouſly did ſlander this Diuine myracle, affirming that the efficient and principall worker thereof was <hi>Beelzebub,</hi> a moſt abhominable and filthy Diuell, by whoſe power Chriſt as his Miniſter did caſt out Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uels: which blaſphemous ſla<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>der againſt their owne conſcience, they did to that end publikely before, deliuer before the people, that by extenuating and diminiſhing of the miracle, they might withdrawe and alienate the mindes of the ſimple people from Chriſt: <hi>Beelze<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bub</hi> ſignifieth <hi>dominum ſeuregem muſca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rum,</hi> it was the God or Idoll of <hi>Accaron,</hi> or <hi>Ekron,</hi> 2. <hi>Rog.</hi> 1.3. with whom <hi>Ahazi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ah,</hi> contrarie to the word of the Lord conſulted: <hi>Baal</hi> was a common name of all the Idols, which were worſhipped
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:11726:14"/>of the infidell nations that bordered vpon <hi>Palestina,</hi> or <hi>Iurie:</hi> the <hi>Caldeans</hi> called it <hi>Bece,</hi> adding for difference ſake ſome other name, as <hi>Beelphegor,</hi> the Idoll of the <hi>Moabite, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>alpear,</hi> the Idoll of the <hi>Amonite. &amp;c.</hi> This Idoll was called <hi>Beelzebub,</hi> becauſe of the multitude of flies, that ſwarmed about the Temple of this Idoll, becauſe of the many ſacrifices which there were ſlaine. The Iewes in contempt did call the Diuell by this name, <hi>the prince of the Dinels:</hi> becauſe he is the prince that ruleth in the ayre, <hi>the Prince of the dark<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe of this world. Epheſ.</hi> 2. <hi>&amp;</hi> 6. and had <hi>ſub Vexillo ſuo, exercitum diabolorum,</hi> like flies ſwarming in the ayre. 3. <hi>verſe</hi> 16. In others which tempted him, <hi>ſeeking a ſigne from heauen:</hi> and theſe were of the <hi>Scribes</hi> and <hi>Phariſies, Mat.</hi> 12: which were not aſhamed by exte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nuating to calumniate this notable myracle, <hi>collatione imparium,</hi> crauing a more excellent myracle to be ſhew<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed in the skie, either that he ſhould raiſe vp thunder, as in the time of <hi>Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>muell,</hi> 1. <hi>Sam.</hi> 12. or to call for fire from
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:11726:14"/>heauen as <hi>Eliah</hi> did, 1. <hi>Reg.</hi> 18. or to make the Sunne to ſtand ſtill. <hi>Ioſ.</hi> 10. or the Sunne to goe backward, 2 <hi>Reg.</hi> 20. or to raine downe Manna from heauen as in the Deſart: but this they craued to a peruerſe end, that they might take occaſion hereby to blaſpheme, and the more quarrell with him: and ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore Chriſt called them an <hi>euil, and ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ulterous generation, Mat.</hi> 12. And theſe are the effects of this myracle, <hi>per acci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dens,</hi> proceeding from the peruerſe ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lice and hatred of the <hi>Scribes</hi> and <hi>Pha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſies.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>Obſer. &amp; Doct.</head>
               <p>HEere obſcrue, out of the 15. <hi>chap.</hi> 16. <hi>verſ.</hi> that nothing can bee ſafe from the viperous teeth of the <hi>Sycophaut,</hi> as we may ſee in the diuers iudgements, which the beholders of this myracle had of Chriſt. The ſame chaunced to <hi>Iohn Baptiſt, Mat.</hi> 11. to <hi>Steuen, Act.</hi> 7. to <hi>Paul,</hi> whom for prea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ching of Chriſt, they ſought to kill. <hi>Act.</hi> 9. and at this day, this is too com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:11726:15"/>in the world, for there are not wanting certaine peruerſe, criticall, and malicious, maleuolent, ce<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſurers, which are readie to giue their peruerſe iudge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments of good men, and to traduce whatſoeuer they ſpeake, or doe well, i<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitating <hi>Xoilus</hi> heerein: who being asked why hee ſpake euill of all men: anſwered, <hi>quoniam malefacere, Cum ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lim non poſſim. Aelian. va<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>hiſt. lib.</hi> 11. but as long as thou doeſt well, feare no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing, the bitings of viperous tongues, thinke that the ſame meaſure was of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fered vnto Chriſt, <hi>the ſeruant is not grea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter then his Maiſter, if they haue called the Maiſter of the houſe, &amp;c. Mat.</hi> 10. imitate <hi>Plato</hi> heerein, who when it was tolde him that many rayled vpon him, an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwered: At <hi>ego ſic viuam, vt illis fide<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> non habeatur.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="2">2 Note here the nature of the wic<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ked; there is no vertue ſo excellent, no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing ſo well done, nothing ſo worthi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly commended, and extolled by the voice of all good-men, which the wic<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ked do not carp at, &amp; diſpraiſe: euen as if he put a ſtaffe, or a peece of timber
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:11726:15"/>halfe way into the water, that part which is in the water, ſeemeth crooked and broken, and the other ſtraite, when indeede it is all alike ſtraite: ſo the ſame action which to an vpright iudgement, ſeemeth well done, and praiſe worthy, to the wicked it ſeemeth crooked and defectiue; not that it is ſo, but by reaſon of their depraued and corrupt iudgement, which deceiueth them, becauſe they looke into the acti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons of others, through the water of en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uie and malice. If thou be humble and lowly, they will iudge thee abiect and vile; if patient, white-liuered, and a daſtard: if ſtudious, an hypocrite: if frugall, a nigard and couetous: if ſilent, they wil iudge thee a foole: if talkatiue, a babler: if deuoute, a diſſembler: if thou doe iuſtice, they will count thee cruell: if pittifull, remiſſe, and corrupt: if milde, they will contemne thee: if li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>berall, they will count thee prodigall: if ſparing, a myzer. &amp;c. And nothing may be ſo well done, but that enuious and wicked men, will take occaſion thereby to backbite and ſlander thee:
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:11726:16"/>euen as a great Riuer, receiueth into it ſelfe all other Riuers that come: and the fire conuerteth into it ſelfe all things it taketh: the Serpent eateth the ſweete flower, and conuerteth it into poyſon, out of which the Bee ſucketh honie: ſo the wicked at the verie ſame thing take occaſion to murmure, and diſhonour God; by which the godly are incited to loue, praiſe, and ſerue the Lord. For when Chriſt did many my<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>racles, the high Prieſts and Phariſies, conſulted how they might put him to death. Now, if thou demand of the high Prieſts and Phariſies, why they would kill Chriſt, 1. they will anſwere, <hi>for this man doth many miracles, Io.</hi> 11. But if thou aske of <hi>Peter, Iames, Iohn,</hi> and the reſt of the Diſciples, why they be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leeue in Chriſt, forſake all that they haue and follow him; they will alſo ſay; <hi>becauſe he doth many myracles,</hi> which none but the <hi>Mesſias</hi> could doe, there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore we beleeued in him, followe, and ſerue him. If you aske why the people did praiſe &amp; extoll Chriſt; they would ſay, <hi>becauſe the dumbe ſpake, &amp;c.</hi> But if
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:11726:16"/>ye ask the Phariſies why they mocke, and blaſpheme Chriſt, they will alſo ſay, <hi>becauſe the dumbe ſpake, &amp;c.</hi> What is the cauſe why this one myracle brin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>geth forth ſuch contrarie effects? ſure<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly becauſe the hearts of both are di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uers, and different. Whereby it com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>meth to paſſe, that what to the one is a medicine and preſent remedie, to the other is a deadly poyſon.</p>
               <p>O that many alſo at this day were not like vnto theſe <hi>Phariſies,</hi> which when they ſhould bee conuerted by Chriſts myracles, wonne with his benefits, and their hearts mollified, and euen melt with the loue of God, they take occaſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on thereby to become worſe, and more obdurate in their ſinne: Is it not an in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eſtimable benefite, that when thou committeſt ſo many, and great ſinnes, yet God patiently ſuffereth thee, ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pecting thy conuerſion? this goodnes of God which ſhould ſo enflame thy minde with his loue, &amp; ſo binde thy af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fection vnto him, that thou ſhouldeſt not dare to offend, ſo louing and mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cifull a God thou abuſeſt to preſume
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:11726:17"/>the more boldly to commit the grea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter ſinne, adding without any feare, ſinne vpon ſinne, and ſaieſt God is mercifull, hee is a good God, he came into the world, ſuffered death vp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on the croſſe to ſaue ſinners. Indeede he is infinitely mercifull, elſe would he not ſuffer thee to make his mercie, and goodneſſe, an occaſion of ſinne, and a cauſe of thy further wickedneſſe, and the croſſe which he endured to deſtroy the Kingdome of the Diuell; to take occaſion thereby, the more boldly to ſinne, and to vphold the Kingdome of the Diuell. Knoweſt thou not (O wrech) that this bountifulneſſe of God <hi>leadeth thee to repentance? but thou after &amp;c. Rom.</hi> 2. <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="3">3 Heere obſcrue; The monſtrous ingratitude of man towards God, which may be conſidered, not onely in that they are made the worſe by Gods bene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fits, but alſo by the circumſtance of time: for at that time when they ſhould eſpecially be conuerted, and admire the workes of God, at the ſame verie time, malice poſſeſſing their hearts,
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:11726:17"/>they did murmure &amp; blaſpheme. The tongue of man is ſcarce able to vtter how great the vnthankfulneſſe of man is; which the greater the benefits are which they receiue, the leſſe doe they feare to offend God. So the Iſraelites while God on the Mount was deliue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring lawes vnto <hi>Moſes,</hi> for their good; they were making a golden calfe in the Vallie, to prouoke him to wrath with their Idolatrie. So Chriſt, when he was at his laſt Supper, inſtituting the holy Sacrament of his bodie and blood, for the benefit and comfort of man; at the verie ſame time they were conſulting together how to betray him: which time the <hi>Ap.</hi> 1. <hi>Cor.</hi> 11. noteth, when he ſaith, <hi>Our Lord Ieſus Christ in the ſame night, &amp;c.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>And no leſſe monſtrous is the ingra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>titude of many now adaies, which while they ſit at their play, ſwearing and blaſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pheming the name of God, and com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitting other greeuous ſinne; in the meane time is God creating, and pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uiding for their ſuſtenance and bene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fite the fruits of the earth, and powring
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:11726:18"/>his bleſſings vpon them, whiles they are crucifying <hi>the Sonne of God againe to themſelues, and making a mocke of him, Heb.</hi> 6. O deteſtable ingratitude, &amp;c.</p>
               <p n="4">4 Note heere, how farre different the iudgement of God is from the iudgement of men: The Phariſies in the opinion of men were reputed ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, and righteous men, and the com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon people, ſimple, and fooliſh; yet the ſpirit of God heere ſaith, that the <hi>Phariſies,</hi> were moſt wicked and blaſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phemous ſinners. We learne heere, to examine our owne conſciences, &amp; not to content our ſelues with the praiſe of men, for according to their fauour, or hatred, they approue euill, and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demne what is good: <hi>plebs eſt moroſa lage<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                     <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>do, ille bene de te dicet, at ille male:</hi> He of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten erreth in iudgemen which liſtneth to the voices of the people: hatred and fauour, are 2. partiall iudges. <hi>Errat a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mans pariter dum iudicat, errat et oſor namque odium fallit, failit &amp; omnis amor.</hi> Saith one. <hi>I paſſe very litle to be iudged of you, or of mans iudgement,</hi> 1. <hi>Cor.</hi> 4.</p>
               <p n="5">5 The Phariſies, are an example vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:11726:18"/>vs of the wretched and abiect eſtate of that man which is forſaken of God; how headlong they fall into all grie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uous ſinne. This vſe let vs make of it, that when we ſee men to fall into hor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rible ſinne, without any feeling of con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcience, let vs thinke that we our ſelues ſhould fall into the ſame or greater, if God ſhould giue vs ouer, or take his grace from vs: let vs euer haue before our cies theſe examples of Gods iudge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments, to ſtirre vp the feare of God in our hearts, that we may learne to know our ſelues, how inſufficient we are of our ſelues, if the hand of God-ſhould not hold vs vp; <hi>Let him that ſtandeth take heede least he fall,</hi> 1. <hi>Cor.</hi> 10. Where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore let euery good Chriſtian, pray with the princely Prophet, <hi>Pſ.</hi> 51. <hi>Caſt me not away from thy preſence, and take not thy ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly ſpirit from me:</hi> without him we cannot ſtand, without him we fall into all kind of wickedneſſe, learne then to hate ſinne which <hi>ſeparateth betwixt God and vs, and hideth his face from vs. Eſ.</hi> 59.</p>
               <p n="6">6 In that the Phariſies lyed, ſpeak<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing contrarie to their owne conſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence;
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:11726:19"/>let vs learne to hate all lying and falſhoode. For it is written, <hi>Pſ.</hi> 5. <hi>Thou ſhalt deſtroy all them that ſpeake lyes:</hi> At the generall flood God deſtroyed the whole world, but ſaued <hi>Noe</hi> and his fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mily, he burned <hi>Sodome,</hi> but ſpared <hi>Lot.</hi> He tooke into his ſocietie <hi>Peter,</hi> an of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fender, <hi>Paule</hi> a perſecutor, <hi>Magdeline</hi> a ſinner, &amp;c. But we find not that he ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitted any lyar.</p>
               <p>Hell (ſaith the wiſe man) <hi>is better then an euill tongue. Ecc.</hi> 28. For hell fire tor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>menteth but the wicked and the dam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned, but an euill tongue hurteth both good and bad. <hi>Who ſo harkeneth thereto, ſhall neuer find rest, nor dwell quietly. Ibid.</hi> The <hi>heart of fooles is in their mouth, but the mouth of the wiſe is in their heart, Ecc.</hi> 22. The tongue ſhould follow the heart, the heart and reaſon ſhould goe before the tongue, as the guide to di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rect and gouerne euerie word, leaſt the tongue runne at randome: <hi>linqua tan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quam calamus eſſe debet, qui per ſe nihil fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cit,</hi> no farther then it is moued by the Scribe, that it be not exorbitant from the rule and order of Chriſtian charitie,
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:11726:19"/>and truth, &amp;c.</p>
               <p n="7">7 Out of the 14. <hi>verſ.</hi> we learne (in the cenſure of the people) that not<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>withſtanding the malicious carping of wicked men, there are not wanting ſome which will iudge truely, and ſin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerely of the ſayings and doings of o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers: for the word of God is neuer preached in vaine, <hi>Eſa.</hi> 55. <hi>Our labour is not in vaine in the Lord.</hi> 1. <hi>Cor.</hi> 15. Here is a great comfort, to all Preachers, that they be not diſcoraged in their calling, whe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the malignant co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>panie do contra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dict them, ſlander, hate, and raile vpon them: for alwaies from the beginning the greater part were the worſt, which <hi>ferrea quada<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> peruicacia</hi> did oppoſe them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelues againſt the ſeruants of God, and lade his Miniſters with ſcoffes, and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>proaches, for reprouing their beloued ſinne: Let vs not marueile, nor be diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maide heereat, ſeeing Chriſt himſelfe could not be free from ſuch malicious detractors, &amp;c.</p>
               <p>Laſtly, <hi>ex verſ.</hi> 16. In that they requi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red a ſigne from heauen, I obſerue, There are at this day which expect
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:11726:20"/>myracles to confirme the Doctrine of the Goſpell: whom with Chriſt we may anſwere, <hi>Mat.</hi> 12. An <hi>euill &amp; adulterous generation ſeeketh aſigne, &amp;c.</hi> Myracles in the primitiue Church were neceſſarie, <hi>vt quae introitus ſunt at fide,</hi> (ſaith <hi>Greg. li.</hi> 27. <hi>Mor. &amp; infidelium cauſa maxime fiunt.</hi> But now we neede them not, becauſe our Doctrine is not new, but confir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med by the Apoſtles, with diuers ſignes &amp; myracles, and gifts of the ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly Ghoſt. <hi>lib.</hi> 2. Whoſoeuer therefore (ſaith <hi>Aug. li.</hi> 22. <hi>de ciuitate dei) prodigia quaerit vt credat, ipſe magnum eſt prodigi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>um, cum toto mundo credente non credat.</hi> Many ſuch prodigious ſinners there are in the world which ſeeke ſignes, ſuch are they which wallowing all their life long in their ſinne, preſume vpon mercie at the laſt gaſpe of their life: theſe ſeeke a ſigne of God at the end of their life: when the generall rule of Gods lawe is, <hi>he will reward euerie man according vnto his workes. Rom.</hi> 2. <hi>Pſ.</hi> 62.2. <hi>Cor.</hi> 5. <hi>Vt quimale vixit, malo pereat.</hi> So when thou haſt liued 30.40.60. yeares in all licentiouſneſſe of life, caſting the
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:11726:20"/>fear of God behind thee, ſinning againſt thine owne conſcience, thou preſumeſt vpon the late repentance of the laſt houre of thy life, and thinkeſt that to be ſufficient: why doeſt thou not feare the wrath of God, and perſwade thy ſelfe rather, that thou ſhalt die in thy ſinnes, which all thy life time thou haſt frequented? doeſt thou not knowe, that repentance is the gift of God? and that it is not in thine owne power? why doſt thou not repent betime, whils the long ſufferance of God inuiteth thee to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pentance? why doeſt thou loſe the gol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>den opportunitie of time, that God of his mercie offereth thee, and in <hi>vtram<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>que aurem dormi,</hi> heaping ſinne vpon ſinne, as if one moments repentance (which yet is not in thine owne power) ſhould make amends for all? Incredi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble ſurely is thy madneſſe: What is this but to tempt God? 1. What is this but to ſeeke a ſigne from heauen? 2. Thin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>keſt thou that God is tyed to thy plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure, to open to thee the doore of hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen, which all thy life long didſt rebell againſt him, and hadſt thy will alwaies
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:11726:21"/>croſſing to his?</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>Pars tertia. Chriſts Apologie.</head>
               <p>FRom the 17. <hi>verſ. vſque ad.</hi> 27. is de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcribed the Apologie of Chriſt, a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt the calumniation of the Pha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſies; impiouſly aſcribing this myracle vnto <hi>Beelzebub;</hi> Chriſts generall <hi>theme is: I doe not caſt out Diuels through Beelze<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bub.</hi> To the proofe whereof he vſeth in order foure arguments. The firſt whereof is taken <hi>ab effectu diſcordia,</hi> conſiſting <hi>traiectione partium, &amp; compli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>catione ſyltogiſmi, ac porſyllogiſmi.</hi> The principall <hi>Syllogiſme</hi> is thus: If through <hi>Beelzebub</hi> I caſt out diuels, Sathan is deuided againſt himſelfe.</p>
               <p>But Sathan is not deuided againſt himſelfe: therefore I caſt not out Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uels through <hi>Beelzebub.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>The <hi>Connex</hi> of the propoſition is plaine by the nature of contraries, which expell and kill one the other. The aſſumption hee proueth by a <hi>pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſyllogiſme</hi> thus:</p>
               <p>If Sathan bee deuided againſt him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe,
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:11726:21"/>his kingdome cannot ſtand im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moueable, but the kingdome of Sathan ſtandeth immoueable.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Ergo,</hi> Sathan is not diuided againſt himſelfe. The propoſition of this <hi>Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſyllogiſme</hi> is proued <hi>A genere, per compae<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rationem ſimilium,</hi> taken from king<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>domes, or houſes which by mutuall diuiſion and diſſention come to mine and deſtruction. The 2. <hi>Arg. verſ.</hi> 19. Is taken <hi>ab exemplo pari,</hi> of them which among the Iewes had the gift of caſting out Diuels, whom the Phariſies con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſed to caſt out Diuels by the power of God. Theſe were the Apoſtles, and 70. Diſciples: hee calleth them their <hi>children,</hi> becauſe they were borne and bred among the Iewes; to whom the Lord gaue power ouervncleane ſpirits. <hi>Luc.</hi> 9. the argument is thus.</p>
               <p>If I by <hi>Beelzebub</hi> caſt out Diuels, then your children alſo by him doe caſt them out: but your children doe not caſt them out through <hi>Beelzebub.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Ergo,</hi> neither doe I.</p>
               <p>The conſequent of the propoſition, is not ſet downe in expreſſe words, but
<pb n="34" facs="tcp:11726:22"/>yet is inſinuated with a figuratiue inter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rogation, by whom, &amp;c. The aſſumpti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on is omitted, as granted by them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelues, for they themſelues affirmed that by the power of God they caſt out Diuells. And therefore hee ſaith, <hi>they ſhall be your Iudges.</hi> That is, by their owne confeſſion, and the confeſſion of their children, they be co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>uinced in the iudgement, that againſt their owne conſcience, they haue moſt maliciouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly aſcribed this myracle to the Diuell. By the ſame argument alſo he conclu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deth that he caſteth out Diuells by the power of God: in this manner.</p>
               <p>If your children by the power of God caſt out Diuells, by the ſame pow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er doe I caſt them out: but your chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren by the power of God caſt out Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uels; therefore I by the power of God caſt them out.</p>
               <p>Which concluſion hee amplifieth, <hi>verſ.</hi> 20. <hi>But if I by the finger of God, caſt them out, &amp;c.</hi> Where, by the finger of God, hee vnderſtandeth the ſpirit of God, as <hi>Mat.</hi> 12.28. Explaineth it. By the kingdome of God, is vnderſtood
<pb n="35" facs="tcp:11726:22"/>the kingdome of the <hi>Mesſias.</hi> He rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoneth from the immediate proper effects, to ſhewe the cauſe from the be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nefits and myracles, onely proper to the <hi>Mesſias,</hi> he proueth himſelfe to be the <hi>Mesſias,</hi> &amp; ſo by their owne con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſion he inferreth, becauſe hee caſt out Diuells by the finger of God. They ought vndoubtedly to know that the kingdome of the <hi>Mesſias</hi> is come vnto them, and is begunne among them.</p>
               <p>The 3. argument is conceiued, <hi>verſ.</hi> 21. &amp; 22. And is taken <hi>ab effectis, ſimili<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tudine bellica,</hi> of a ſtrong man armed, which by a more ſtronger is expelled and caſt out of his Pallace. Where 1. by the ſtrong man armed, is meant the the Diuell, 2. his Pallace, are wicked men, which he hath vnder his gouern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment; his armour wherein he truſted, is the great power of the Diuell. The argument may bee thus concluded in the 2. figure.</p>
               <p>He that ouerco<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>meth, and caſteth out another by his owne power, is ſtron<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger then he that is caſt out and ouer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>come: but I by my owne power doe
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:11726:23"/>ouercome, and caſt out Diuels.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Ergo,</hi> I am ſtronger then the Diuels, and by conſequent, I doe not caſt out Diuels through <hi>Beelzebub.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>The 4. argument is taken <hi>a contrariis rugnantium perſonarum ſtudus, &amp; effectis: verſ.</hi> 23. <hi>He that is not with me, &amp;c.</hi> It is a prouerbiall <hi>gnome,</hi> or ſentence which <hi>ſllogiſticè</hi> in 1. fig. may thus be inferred.</p>
               <p>Whoſoeuer in al things is againſt me, and contrarie vnto me, by his power I cannot caſt out Diuels: but Sathan in all things is contrarie to me, <hi>Ergo, &amp;c.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Betwixt Chriſt and Sathan, there is alwaies <hi>bellum hostile,</hi> Chriſt is the God of truth, the Deuill is the father of lies: what Chriſt buildeth, the Diuell labou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reth to pull downe: what fellowſhip then betweene <hi>Chriſt</hi> and <hi>Beliai? &amp;c.</hi> 2. <hi>Cor.</hi> 6. This alſo he proueth by an al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>legoricall ſimilitude, adorned by a <hi>Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſopopaeia,</hi> of an enemie which with an in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fatigable ſtudie, laboureth to inuade, and take poſſeſſion of his aduerſary. <hi>Ab adiuncto pertinaci ſtudio diaboli, et à cauſis adiuuantibus. verſ.</hi> 24.25.26. <hi>When the vncleane ſpirit, &amp;c.</hi> 1. By the vncleane
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:11726:23"/>ſpirit, hee vnderſtandeth the Diuell' which is called vncleane, 1. <hi>Ab abiunctis</hi> by reaſon of his naturall vncleannes: 2. <hi>Exeffectis,</hi> becauſe he maketh them vncleane, whom hee polluteth with finne. 2. <hi>Exit iſte,</hi> he goeth forth, when by the vertue of Chriſt, and of his word through repentance hee is caſt out. 3 Hee walketh through drie places: by drie places, moſt interpreters vnder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtand, partly the Godly, and partly the wicked and infidels; for in neither of theſe, he ſetteth his reſt; for when by repentance, and the grace of Chriſt, he is caſt out of the heart of the penitent ſinner, hee inceſſantly walketh about hunting after his prey, and catching af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter ſoules, &amp; aſſaulteth the godly, ſeek<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing to poſſeſſe, and to enter into their hearts: for the hearts of the godly are called (ſaith one) <hi>loca arida,</hi> becauſe <hi>ni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hil melle, nihil diſſolutum habent: ſed om<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nia ſolida &amp; firma quae arida &amp; ſolicita ſunt</hi> (ſaith <hi>Theophilact</hi>) &amp; are warie and carefull of their ſoules; ſeeking reſt: that is, to batter downe, and to winne the fort of their hearts, and to make
<pb n="38" facs="tcp:11726:24"/>it a dwelling place of all wickedneſſe, but findeth none; they yeelde not to his ſuggeſtions, they reſiſt him ſtedfaſt in faith. 1. <hi>Pet.</hi> 5. <hi>They ſtand against the aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſaults of the Diuell, being ſtrong in the Lord, and in the power of his might. Epheſ.</hi> 6. <hi>They giue no way vnto him.</hi> So the hearts of the godly are the ſolide, firme, and drie places, which will admit no noyſome humour of ſuggeſtions, whereon the Diuell may faſten his peſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tilent ſeede of temptations, there is no moiſture of diſſolute liuing to nouriſh it, &amp;c. And ſo <hi>minus gratum eſt hoc daemo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nibus habitaculum,</hi> as the drie places are vnfit to inhabite, (ſaith another.) &amp;c.</p>
               <p>They which take <hi>loca arid<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> &amp; inaquo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>,</hi> for the minde and hearts of wicked men, interprete it thus. The hearts of the wicked are called drie places, that we might vnderſtand their vnhappie eſtate and condition, they are compa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red <hi>ſqualentis cremi ſterilitati;</hi> becauſe there is found in them, no culture of life, no ſtudie of godlineſſe, no fruit of good workes, no humor of pietie, mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cie, deuotion, but all things are drie,
<pb n="39" facs="tcp:11726:24"/>barraine, and vnfruitfull. In thoſe the Diuell ſeeketh reſt, and findeth none: for as a couetous man, is neuer ſatiſfied with that he hath, but greedily gapeth after more: (for hee is more grieued with the deſire of other mens, then hee reioyceth in that which is his owne) ſo our ghoſtly enemie, which is inſati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able and greedie of ſoules, reſteth not ſatisfied with them, whom hee hath made alreadie his owne, but moſt ea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gerly gapeth after that which belong<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth not vnto him: that is, which per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taine vnto God, he ſtill crieth like the daughter of the Horſleach, <hi>affer, affer, Pro.</hi> 30. More, more, <hi>nec enim illos quae<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit quos iamſubegit, hos enim captiuos te<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>net: illos pergit laceſſere in quibus Chriſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tum cernit habitare. Cypri.</hi> Now when in theſe places he findeth no reſt (for with infatigable labour, he gapeth and ſee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>keth to inſnare and catch others) he re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolueth to returne againe vnto his houſe whence he came out: and fin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding it emptie, <hi>Mat.</hi> 12. <hi>ſwept and gar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſhed.</hi> That is, made readie &amp; prepared, as a houſe is trimmed, decked, and a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dorned, inuiteth gueſts to enter into it:
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:11726:25"/>So when the Diuell ſeeth men ſecure, negligent of their ſaluation, when they keepe not their eyes, cares, tongue, nor the reſt of their ſences, (which are as it were the doores of the ſoule.) When (I ſay) they keepe not carefull watch ouer their ſoules, and are deſtitute of their ſpirituall armor, faith, &amp;c. Prayer, diuine meditations. The enemie is hereby inuited, to enter into his former habitation. The 7. o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther ſpirits worſe then himſelfe: are many more infernall ſpirits, by whoſe power and operation the hearts of wic<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ked men (by the iuſt iudgement of God, puniſhing their ſecuritie) are blinded, hardened, and holden cap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiue. All theſe helliſh armie combine themſelues together, euerie one in his place, to aſſault, &amp; inuade the walles of the ſpirituall Caſtle of the ſoule; one ſtirring him forward to pride; another pricking him to couetouſneſſe; ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther incenſing with a deſire of reuenge; another alluring him to lecherie; ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther drawing him to enuie, &amp;c. So that this wreched man, if he reſiſt ſome of
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:11726:25"/>theſe aſſaults, he may yet be taken with the other. This place containeth a moſt graue admonition, to beware of carnall ſecuritie: it is directed general<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly vnto all Chriſtians, but eſpecially vnto thoſe which make a reuolt from God, that they ſhould bee carefully carefull to beware of the impudent malice of this ſo vncleane ſpirit: The reaſons heere he vſeth, are 2; 1. <hi>ab ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iuncto ſtudio,</hi> of the Diuell and his com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plices, that they haue to ſeeke the de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtruction of mankind. <hi>verſ.</hi> 24. The 2. is <hi>a perieuloſo euentu. The laſt state of that man is worſe then the firſt. For if they after they haue eſcaped from the filthineſſe of the world, through the knowledge of the Lord, and of the Sa. I. C. are yet intangled againe therein, and ouercome, the later end of that man is worſe then the beginning.</hi> 2. <hi>Pet.</hi> 2.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>Obſ. &amp; doct.</head>
               <p>
                  <hi>EX verſ.</hi> 17.1. <hi>In that Chriſt knewe their thoughts,</hi> he plainly ſhewed himſelfe to be the true God, he is <hi>Cardiognoſtes, he is omniſcius,</hi> hee ſear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cheth euery ſecret corner of the hart, &amp; hath no need that any ſhould teſtifie
<pb n="42" facs="tcp:11726:26"/>of men. <hi>Io.</hi> 2. O that the ſinner would reuolue this alwayes in his minde, that God ſeeth all things, euen his ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cret thoughts: There is none ſo ſhame<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſſe and impudent, that will dare to commit thoſe ſinnes before men, which yet without bluſhing, they feare not daily to commit in the open ſight of God; If God knoweth the thoughts of thy heart, how (thinkeſt thou) ſhall he be ignorant of thy wicked deedes? Heare (O fooliſh man) what God ſaith to <hi>Samuel,</hi> 1. <hi>Sa.</hi> 16. <hi>God ſeeth not as man ſeeth, for man looketh on the outward ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pearance, but God beholdeth the heart.</hi> But ſuch is the blindneſſe of wicked men, and the ſtupide fooliſhneſſe that ſinne cauſeth, that ſeeing he ſeeth not God, he ſuppoſeth that God ſeeth not him. <hi>Eliſha</hi> was inuironed about with angels, but his ſeruant ſaw it not, 2. <hi>Reg.</hi> 6. So aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure thy ſelfe, that whatſoeuer thou doeſt, God and his Angels beholdeth thee, though thou ſeeſt them not. Learne heere to feare the Lord, ſeeing we haue to doe with him, who is both a iudge and a witneſſe, to whom our ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie
<pb n="43" facs="tcp:11726:26"/>thoughts are manifeſt, much more our wicked actions, &amp;c. Heerein they are like children, which winking with their eyes ſee no bodie, they think that they are ſeene of none. 2. <hi>vorſ. &amp;</hi> 17. <hi>Euery kingdome diuided, &amp;c.</hi> Seeing there is an indiſſoluble conſent of wic<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ked ſpirits in vpholding their King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome: let vs alſo be inuincible, and of one minde, in maintaining the vnitie of the Church, through the bande of peace, <hi>Eph.</hi> 4. <hi>Be of like affection one to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward another. Rom.</hi> 12. <hi>Be of one minde, liue in peace.</hi> 2. <hi>Cor.</hi> 13. Which inuincible bande of Chriſtian vnitie, as it wonder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fully furthereth the courſe of the Goſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pell: ſo diſſentions, ſtrife, and conten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, greatly hindreth the ſame: If yee bite and deuoure one another, take heede, &amp;c. <hi>Gal.</hi> 5. <hi>quae priuatae inimicitiae, maximo ſemper detrimento eccleſiam affe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerunt, &amp; relligionem in multas ſectas diſſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cuerunt.</hi> As truely ſaith <hi>Nicephorus, lib.</hi> 11. <hi>Hiſt. Eccleſ.</hi> Let vs beware therefore (brethren) that through our fault no ſchiſmes, and rents, may ariſe in the Church.</p>
               <p n="3">
                  <pb n="28" facs="tcp:11726:27"/> 3 Seeing no Citie, or houſe or king<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome, if it be diuided againſt it ſelf can ſta<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d. We are taught that co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>cord in eue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry ſtate of life is to be imbraced: as <hi>Me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nenius Agippa</hi> in <hi>Liu. l.</hi> 2. a Romane, wiſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly confeſſed, when by an elegant Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>logie of the diſſention of the members of the bodie, reduced to vnitie the <hi>Senate,</hi> and people of <hi>Rome,</hi> being at diſcord. Againe, King <hi>Mycipſa,</hi> being about to die, in a fatherly affection, ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>horting his children to concord, com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mended vnto them this ſentence, wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thy to bee written in golden letters: <hi>Concordia res paruae creſcunt, diſcordia magna dilabuntur. Saluſt.</hi> Teaching all parents at their death, to bequeath co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>corde vnto their children, the beſt le<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gacie they may leaue them; As <hi>Plut. de garru.</hi> reporteth of <hi>Scylurus</hi> the <hi>Scythi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>an,</hi> who had 80. Sonnes; who at his death bad his Sonnes to bring him a ſheafe of arrowes, which he deliuered vnto his Sonnes, commanding each of them, to breake them in peeces all at once: which when not one of them could doe, hee himſelfe pulling them
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:11726:27"/>out, one, by one, eaſily brake them be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore their faces; ſhewing them by this parable, the truth of that which <hi>Salo.</hi> teacheth, <hi>Pro.</hi> 18. <hi>That a brother vnited to a brother, is like an impugnable Citie:</hi> and their counſailes, like the barre of a Pallace, which cannot be broken: for if their contentions bee ſuch, much more their concorde and vnitie. But to learne this point, I may ſend you as the Apoſtle did the Corinthians, to the ſchoole of nature, 1. <hi>Cor.</hi> 11. <hi>Nonne ipſa vos natura hoc docet?</hi> This reciprocall and mutuall concord, nature her ſelfe teacheth vs in the fabrike and ſtructure of the bodie, for ſhe hath made moſt parts, 2. or double, <hi>germana &amp; gemella,</hi> as hands, feet, eyes, eares, noſtrils, ſigni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fying hereby that all theſe for mutuall help, not hurt, are ſo diſtinguiſhed, that they might the better ſuccour &amp; helpe one the other. Now if the hand which God created to helpe one the other, neglecting this, ſhould hurt one the o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther; or if the feete which were created to beare one anothers burthen, leauing this, ſhould ſuppla<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t one the other: or if
<pb n="46" facs="tcp:11726:28"/>the eyes which like <hi>Caleb,</hi> and <hi>Ioſuah,</hi> are fellowe ſpies in the <hi>Microcoſme,</hi> and little world of the bodie, ſhould not looke for one anothers helpe, but looke aſquint at the good of each o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, were not this vnnatural and mon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrous in the bodie? how much more monſtrous is it for vs, which are bre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thren and Chriſtians, all members of one bodie, to liue in diſcord, and ſeeke the hurt one of another? For the nea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rer the cauſe is of coniunction, the greater muſt needes bee the wrong which doth diſſipate it. The woundes which <hi>Brutus</hi> his friend gaue to <hi>Caeſar,</hi> went nearer his heart, then all the ſtabs of his foes: <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, (quoth hee) and thou alſo my ſonne <hi>Brutus.</hi> This made <hi>Dauid</hi> complaine, <hi>Pſ.</hi> 55. <hi>If mine enemie, &amp;c.</hi> So monſtrous and barba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rous a thing it is, to beare enmitie, with them eſpecially, to whom we owe moſt loue and affection. Where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore as <hi>Salo.</hi> ſent the ſluggard to the Emmet to ſchoole, that hee might learne to laboure, <hi>Pro.</hi> 6. <hi>Eſay,</hi> the vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gratefull to the Oxe and Aſſe, to learne
<pb n="47" facs="tcp:11726:28"/>thankfulneſſe, <hi>Eſa.</hi> 1. <hi>Ieremie</hi> the neg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lecter of ſeaſon, to the ſtorke and crane, the Turtle, and the Swallow, to learne the opportunitie of time, <hi>Iere.</hi> 8. and our Sauiour the worldling, to the Ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uens to learne Gods prouidence, and contentation: <hi>Mat.</hi> 6. So may I ſend the refractarie, and contentious per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons to behold the frame of the world, which preacheth concorde and vnitie vnto man. We ſee the celeſtiall Orbes and Spheares of heauen, though their motions be diuers, and their reuoluti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons thwartingly croſſing one another (as <hi>Eraſ. in pacis quaerimonia</hi> ſaith) yet are they euer conſtant in the firſt coue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nant of peace, wherein the God of vni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie at firſt placed them. The Elements though in nature contrarie, and in ope<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration oppoſite, (as drought and moi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſture, colde and heate) yet <hi>concordi pace ligantur:</hi> they all conſpire together in a friendly temperature for the preſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uation of mans bodie. The beaſts of the field, the fiſhes of the Sea, the fowles of the ayre, in their proper kinds, <hi>armentatim paſcunt, gregatim na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tant,
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:11726:29"/>turmatim v<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>lant</hi> (ſaith he) feede by heards, ſwimme by companies, flie by flockes, and all to preach concord and vnitie vnto man. The verie Serpents bite not one another. The rauenous fi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhes deuoure none of their owne kind: the moſt greedie birds and beaſts, will not prey vpon their like: and ſhall man more vnnaturall then all other crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures be diuided? ſeeke the ſpoyle one of another, and worſe then the Tygers, Dragons, and Serpents, worke the de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtruction one of another, which yet are bound together by God, with more bands of amitie then all the reſt?</p>
               <p>When God created man, he created him alone, but <hi>vnicum,</hi> as a thing of v<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nitie without diuiſion, (when all other creatures were made couples, &amp; twoes, <hi>Gen.</hi> 1.) Which one though the Creator made 2. by &amp; after creation, yet made he theſe 2. one againe by coniunction of marriage, <hi>vt ſciamus quâm concorditer viuere deberenous. Aug.</hi> 11. <hi>de ciuitate dei cap.</hi> 21. that thereby we might knowe how peaceably, we ſhould liue together in one minde. Wherefore (<hi>brethren let
<pb n="33" facs="tcp:11726:29"/>the ſan<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>e minde,</hi> What? ſhall I ſay with the Apoſtle, <hi>the ſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>e minde that was in Chriſt Ieſus, Phil.</hi> 2. No I dare not, I am out of hope of it, he was ſuch a louer of men, that he laid downe his moſt pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cious life, and ſuffered the moſt igno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minious death, to ſaue man his moſt re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bellious enemie. But if not the ſame, yet let the like minde be in you. <hi>Be ye fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowers of Christ as deare children, &amp; walke in loue, Epheſ.</hi> 5. Nay let but the mind of beaſts to them of their owne kinde, be in you. For where as all mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions of enmitie in them be but ſingle, and peculiar to their owne nature, they all concurre togither in one man, as all riuers runne into the ſea. Man to man is in heade craftie as a Fox; in greedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe like a Wolfe, in fierceneſſe like a Tyger, in tongue as venemous as the Serpent, in their euill eye, as deadly as the Cockatrice; in bloodie hands re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſembling the crueltie of Lions. And whereas the integritie of our forefa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers brought forth this Prouerbe, <hi>Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>o homini Deus.</hi> This corrupt age hath turned <hi>Deus</hi> into <hi>Lupus,</hi> from a preſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer
<pb n="34" facs="tcp:11726:30"/>of man, into a deuourer of man, to ſpoile one the other: nay, <hi>Homo homini Damon,</hi> to imitate the Diuel one towards another in enuie, &amp;c.</p>
               <p>And ſurely what ſhould more linke our mindes together, then the verie name of a Chriſtian, if we had ſpirituall eyes to looke into it? We are all borne of one immortall ſeede, in one wombe of the Church, growing vp in one bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>die to the full ſtature of Chriſt, as mem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bers knit together by one ſpirit, all tra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uailing to one <hi>Chanaan,</hi> and hope of our calling, ſeruing all one Lord, pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſing all one faith, hauing all made the ſame vowe in Baptiſme. <hi>In rebus tam multis conſortium &amp; in vitatam in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>explicabile diſſiaium:</hi> ſayeth one, In ſo many things fellowſhip, and in life no friendſhip? all one bodie, and in the members no ſimpathie? in all one ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit, and in the affections no harmonie? all one hope of heauen, and in coheires no ſimphonie? all one Lord, and in fel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>low ſeruants no vnitie? all one faith, &amp; in opinions no ſimmetrie? all ſworne in one Baptiſme, and in fellow ſouldi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers
<pb n="35" facs="tcp:11726:30"/>no ſymmachie? all adopted by one father, and among brethren no frater<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nitie? ſo many ones and no vnitie? This of all other is <hi>Argumentum maxi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mi monenti,</hi> ſaith a father, the moſt in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ducing motiue, and ſtrongeſt argu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment that may be vnto loue, that we are al by one God &amp; Father made one bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>die, through one ſpirit, to ſerue one Lord, in one faith, and conſecrated to him by one Baptiſme, doe hope all for one glorious inheritance wherevn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to we are called, <hi>Epheſ.</hi> 4. <hi>Behold how good, &amp;c. Pſal.</hi> 133. It is both <hi>bonum &amp; iucundum,</hi> ſaith <hi>Auguſt miſcuit vtile dulci</hi> he hath mingled pleaſantnes to make thee taſt, with good to make thee ſauor this great bleſſing of the Lord: for pleaſantneſſe, he likeneth it to the ſweet ſauour of <hi>Aarons precious oyntment:</hi> for the profit thereof vnto <hi>deaw of Hermon,</hi> and for the happineſſe thereof, hee expreſſeth the promiſe of bleſſed<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe, for there the Lord hath promi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed his bleſſing in this life, and life for euermore in the heauenly King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome.</p>
               <pb n="36" facs="tcp:11726:31"/>
               <p> Which bleſſed vertue of concorde, as it is required in all Chriſtians, if euer they thinke to be partakers of the eter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nall bleſſedneſſe: ſo eſpecially it is co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mended to the wedded eſtate, <hi>for nulli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>us reipoſſesſio coniugaſi pace posſit eſſe iu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cundior.</hi> For they which in this ſtate liue peaceably <hi>futurae iam vitae imaginem quandam referunt quae viſio pacis appella<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tur.</hi> (Saith this father) as contrariwiſe, they which <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>arre among themſelues with priuate contentions and ſtrife, in this life they here begin their hell, and ſhal taſt of a double hel, in this life pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent, &amp; in the life to come. Whoſoeuer would aſpire to this peace, let him craue it of God, who only maketh men to be of one minde in an houſe, and at the beginning of his Church, gathered together a multitude, of the beleeuing in nature diſcrepant and diuers, that they might be one heart, &amp; one ſoule, <hi>Act.</hi> 4. And next, let euerie one re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nounce his owne will and iudgement, eſpecially the wiues, whome God co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mandeth to be ſubiect vnto their huſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bands, otherwiſe if they will ſtifly
<pb n="37" facs="tcp:11726:31"/>ſtand vpon their <hi>ſummum ius</hi> their peace and ſafetie cannot long endure. <hi>Faelices ter &amp; amplius, quos irrupta tenet copula, &amp;c. Hor. lib.</hi> 3. This was the Legacie which Chriſt bequeathed to his children at his departing, peace I leaue with you, my peace I giue vnto you, <hi>Io.</hi> 14. For this he prayed eſpecial<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly vnto the father, <hi>Io.</hi> 17. <hi>That they may be one, as thou a father art in me, and I in thee.</hi> If any Prince trauailing into a far countrie, ſhould giue vnto his Queene and ſpouſe any precious Iewell, as a pledge of his loue, and ſhe after his de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>parting, ſhould contemne and ſet light by it, were ſhe not worthy to be con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demned of monſtrous ingratitude? but this precious iewel Chriſt gaue be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore his departing to his father, which we ſo vilely eſteeme that for the leaſt occaſion we feare not to violate the ſame: how then ſhall we bee thought to haue any part with Chriſt, what aſſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rance that we are his children, or how ſhould we looke to be partakers of his glory, if our wils be ſo ouer-thwart and croſſing to his moſt holy will and diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſition?</p>
               <p n="4">
                  <pb n="38" facs="tcp:11726:32"/> 4 Note that there bee many men now adaies, herein rightly reſembling the diuels, which though they liue in perpetuall ſtrife and enmitie among themſelues, yet to perſecute the godly and innocent, they peaceably combine themſelues together. So <hi>Herode</hi> &amp; <hi>Pi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>late,</hi> though they were at mortall diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>corde, yet they agreed together, to condemne Chriſt, and were made friends, <hi>Luc.</hi> 2. So wicked men though in all other things their natures bee croſſing, yet conſpire they together to doe miſchiefe: and euen ſo as this god<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly peace conſerueth, and corroborateth the kingdome of Chriſt; ſo the per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerſe peace of the wicked, vpholdeth the kingdome of ſathan.</p>
               <p n="5">5 <hi>Ex verſe,</hi> 21. We haue this com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fortable Doctrine: that Chriſt is ſtron<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger then the diuell, which is called the ſtrong armed man, he hath bruiſed his head, <hi>Gen.</hi> 3. He hath iudged him, <hi>Io.</hi> 16. He hath taken away his power ouer vs, he hath diuided the ſpoiles, he hath ſpoyled the principalities, and powers,
<pb n="39" facs="tcp:11726:32"/>and made a ſhew of them openly, <hi>Col.</hi> 2. Sitting at the right hand of the fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, defendeth our cauſe againſt the accuſer of the brethren, <hi>Reue.</hi> 12. <hi>This God of peace ſhall ſhortly treade ſathan vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der our feete. Rom.</hi> 16. Let vs therefore ſtand faſt in the Lord, and feare not, for greater is he that is in vs, then hee that is in the world. 1. <hi>Io.</hi> 4. <hi>Non debet timere hoſtem fortem qui dominum habet fortiorem, Chryſost.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="6">6 Againe, heere is one thing to bee obſerued; in that he ſaith, <hi>when the Diuell keepeth his pallace, the things hee poſſeſſeth are in peace.</hi> Heere is ſhewed the nature of this infernall ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mie, when once he hath poſſeſſed the ſoule of the ſinner, he laboureth by all meanes to bring him to ſecuritie, that without feeling hee may reſt in his ſinne, and as the prouerbe is, <hi>in vtram<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>que aurem dormire,</hi> that if it be poſſible hee may not feele the pricking and ſting of co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſcience, leaſt by repentance hee ſhould eſcape out of his clawes; therefore he endeuoureth to hold him ſtill in this deadly ſleepe of ſinne. And
<pb n="40" facs="tcp:11726:33"/>as they that led the Iſraelites captiue, required of them ſongs and mirth in their heauineſſe, ſaying: <hi>ſing vs one of the ſongs of Sion, Pſal.</hi> 137. So the diuell whe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> he hath brought any into the miſera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble ſeruitude, and captiuitie of ſinne, ſeeketh by all meanes to make him ſing, reioyce, play, and reſt ſecure in his ſinnes, that ſo he might forget the danger and miſerie he is in. To whom (brethren) let vs anſwere as it followeth in the ſame Pſalme: <hi>how ſhall we ſing the Lords ſong in a ſtrange land?</hi> how, ſeeing we are inhabitants of heauen, and haue heere no continuing Citie, but we ſeeke one to come. <hi>Heb.</hi> 13. How (I ſay) in this our pilgrimage, in this place of exile, and miſerie ſhould we reioyce? how ſhould we ſing and <hi>Iubilate</hi> the ſong of mirth, and carnall ſecuritie, ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uing a conſcience clogged with ſinne? dwelling heere in the <hi>Babylon</hi> and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fuſion of ſinne: when we cal to remem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bra<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce, the celeſtiall <hi>Ieruſalem,</hi> the coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trie of the bleſſed, how ſhould we chooſe but with ſighings, gronings, and teares in heart, aſpire vnto the
<pb n="41" facs="tcp:11726:33"/>ſame? But (alas) there are many <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>o drowned in their ſinnes, and detained with ſuch tyrannie in the ſnares of the diuell, that in this moſt wreched ſtate they are ſecure, they reioyce, and ſing, they remember neither the heauenly <hi>Ieruſalem,</hi> the countrie of the bleſſed Saints of God, nor thinke vpon their owne vnhappie ſeruitude; and thus the the diuell holdeth them in quiet and peaceable poſſeſſion. O wretched and moſt cruell peace; <hi>This felicitie is moſt bitter griefe. Eſa.</hi> 38.17. They ſhall find this of truth, <hi>Ierc.</hi> 2.1<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>. <hi>That it is both an euill, and a bitter thing to forſake the Lord their God.</hi> For though outwardly they ſeeme to haue peace with the world and the fleſh, yet inwardly they haue alwayes moſt cruell conflicts, and reſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſſe warre with their paſſions: they ſay peace, peace, when there is no peace, <hi>Iere.</hi> 6. This craftie enemie dea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leth with the ſinner, as we vſe to doe with our gardens or Orchards: when the Trees are yet budding and bloo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ming, and the fruite not yet come to maturitie and ripeneſſe, we vſe no great
<pb n="42" facs="tcp:11726:34"/>care in watching and keeping it: but when the fruite beginneth to come to the expected ripenes, we looke more carefully vnto it. So when thy ſinne beginneth to waxe ripe, and to growe towards hardneſſe of heart, then this enemie watcheth, and is the more care<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full and vigilant of thee, leaſt thou ſhouldeſt hearken to the voice of God, knocking at the doore of thy heart; and open vnto his Diuine inſpirations, vntill thou be come into <hi>profundum peccati</hi> into the deepth of ſinne, and in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to the ripeneſſe of iniquitie, and bee made a fit diſh for the diuels table</p>
               <p>This is the miſerable captiuitie wher<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in hee holdeth the wicked, which yet willingly ſubiect themſelues vnto him, chooſe rather to fight vnder his ban<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner, ſo they may quietly follow their pleaſures for a ſeaſon, then as the good Souldiers of Chriſt valiantly to reſiſt him. And herein they imitate the Iſrae<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lites, which choſe rather to ſubiect themſelues vnto the vniuſt yoke of cruell <hi>Pharoe,</hi> then to ſuſtaine a little labour for the land of Promiſe. <hi>Exod.</hi>
                  <pb n="43" facs="tcp:11726:34"/>16. Sometime the lewde man, or who<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſhwoman, reſolue with themſelues to giue ouer their filthie life, knowing how odious this ſinne is in the ſight of God: now the diuell fearing to looſe his pray beſtirreth him, and ſuggeſteth into the mind of this wretched woman, that if ſhe giue ouer this filthie trade, ſhe ſhall liue in penurie, and want main<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tenance, and that he may in peace poſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeſſe them, he layeth before their eies the ſtrictneſſe of Gods iudgements, the implacableneſſe of his wrath, that re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pentance is now too late, and in vaine, and therefore willeth them to take the preſent fruit of their pleaſures. So hee layeth before the Vſurer, the hardneſſe of the times, the ſweetneſſe of the gaine which without any paines commeth rowling into his bagges, &amp;c. and by no meanes will haue the ſinner to forſake his damnable waies. But (my brethren) let vs ſtoppe our eares to the peſtilent counſailes of this helliſh fiend, conſider that all the pretended impediments of Sathan are in deed but ſtrawes, and fea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers, they appeare to be ſomthing, whe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <pb n="44" facs="tcp:11726:35"/>they are indeed nothing but ſhadowes, let him not with theſe paper-darts ſhake or weaken our confidence in God: hee cannot lie which ſaid, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 37. <hi>Truſt thou in the Lord, and be doing good: dwell in the land, and aſſuredly thou ſhalt be fed.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="7">7. <hi>Verſ.</hi> 23. <hi>He that is not with me is a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt me:</hi> This <hi>gnome</hi> of Chriſt is dili<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gently to be noted: we muſt therefore of neceſſitie ſtande on Chriſts ſide, or on Sathans, wee muſt either ſcrue God or Mammon, aſſent with Chriſt or with Belial, 2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 9. <hi>Nullum eſt hîc ter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tium,</hi> here is no third; for what com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>munio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> hath light with darknes. 2. <hi>Cor.</hi> 6 Harken to this ye <hi>Neutraliſts</hi> which halte betweene two opinions, 1. <hi>Reg.</hi> 18. <hi>Non naſcitur ex bono malum, non magis quâm ex ficu olea,</hi> good cannot ſpring of euill, no more then the oliue of the fig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tree. Saith <hi>Seneca.</hi> 30. <hi>Epiſt. Bonus animus nunquam erranti obſequium accommodat,</hi> A good minde neuer reacheth the hel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ping hand to vphold error. Saith he a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gaine. <hi>Solon</hi> neuer reputeth him a good Citizen, which in a ciuill diſſention would aſſociate himſelfe to neither
<pb n="45" facs="tcp:11726:35"/>part &amp; in diſſenſions of matters of faith ſhall we thinke ſuch to bee good men? God will ſpewe them out of his mouth. <hi>Apoc.</hi> 3.</p>
               <p n="8">8. <hi>Verſ.</hi> 24. When this vncleane ſpirit walking through drie places could find no reſt, to ſettle his habitation there, he reſolueth with himſelfe to returne into his houſe, from whence hee came out: He calleth it his houſe, not by creation, for all things are Gods, but by poſſeſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on. Co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſider here (O wretch) what gueſt thou reiecteſt, and whom thou recey<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ueſt when thou ſerueſt him: thou re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iecteſt God, and admitteſt the Diuell: thou expelleſt life, and receiueſt death: thou flieſt light, and entertaineſt the Prince of darkneſſe. Euen as through <hi>Sauls</hi> diſobedience the ſpirit of God departed from him, preſently the euill ſpirit poſſeſſed him, which horriblie tormented both his bodie and ſoule: which inflamed him with the fire of enuie and ambition, which incenſed him to perſecute innoce<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t <hi>Dauid,</hi> &amp; moſt barbarouſly to murder the prieſts of the Lord, and laſtly to be his owne butcher:
<pb n="46" facs="tcp:11726:36"/>1. <hi>Sam.</hi> 22 to 31. So (brethren) let vs aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure our ſelues, that if we forſake the Lord, he will forſake vs. 2. <hi>Chro.</hi> 15. If we ſuffer ſin to raigne in vs, the ſpirit of God will forſake vs, and then pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſently our hearts are made an habita<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion for the vncleane ſpirit O (brethre<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>) how fearefull and miſerable is the ſtate of that man which is forſaken of God, the fountaine of all goodneſſe, and poſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeſſed of the diuell the authour of all euill? What euill is there that this moſt cruell, and mightie enimie, will not ef<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fect in them whome hee poſſeſſeth? Note here that the diuel ſaith not, I will goe into ſome other houſe: but I will returne into the houſe from whence I came. See here the impudent boldneſſe of this enemie: he preſumeth that the doores of that houſe are alwayes open vnto him. He knoweth that they which haue euer beene accuſtomed to ſinne, caſting aſide al feare, wil eaſily be drawn backe to their vomite, and brought to their olde bias, <hi>and when hee commeth hee findeth it emptie, Mat.</hi> 12. <hi>Swept and garniſhed, Swept, Per conſuetudinem
<pb n="47" facs="tcp:11726:36"/>peccati,</hi> emptie, of faith, good workes, and all holy exerciſes, <hi>per pigritiam, &amp; nogligentiam,</hi> garniſhed with counterfe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>it vertues, <hi>per hypocriſin:</hi> ſaith an auncient writer.</p>
               <p n="1">1. <hi>Swept.</hi> The Broome ſwe epeth a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>way but the duſt, it leaueth the dirt and whatſoeuer ſticketh faſt, it moueth not that. So many will vſe <hi>Verriculo pani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tentiae,</hi> the Broome of repentance, in ſweeping the houſe of their ſoule light<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, and ſuperficially, they leaue ſtill be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hinde their euill cuſtomes, and wicked habite of ſinne which cleaueth faſt vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to them. We ſee many Vſurers will hate adulterie, make conſcience of ſwearing and periurie, &amp;c. Theſe Cobwebs they ſweepe cleane away, but as for the filthy habite, gainfull cuſtome, wicked trade of Vſurie, becauſe it bringeth profite, they leaue that vntouched, their broome reacheth not ſo farre. Like<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe, many adulterers (though wel mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nied) deteſt Vſurie as vtterly vnlawfull, and forbidden of God, vpon paine of damnation. <hi>Pſal.</hi> 15. <hi>Ezech.</hi> 18. &amp;c. They will (perhaps) loath lying, craft oppreſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion,
<pb n="48" facs="tcp:11726:37"/>&amp;c. but as for Adulterie, their belo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued ſinne, which continuall cuſtome hath brought to an habite, that filthy dirt they leaue vnſwept, that cleaueth ſtill faſt to the walles of their ſpirituall houſe. The like may be ſaid of all other accuſtomed ſinne. Theſe are like hypo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>criticall <hi>Naaman,</hi> 2. <hi>King.</hi> 5.18. which when he reſolued to ſerue the God of heauen, hee excepted one thing with God, <hi>The Lord be mercifull to mee</hi> (ſayth he) <hi>in this point.</hi> So the Hypocrites wold faine indent with God, to diſpence with their beloued ſinne, their gainfull ſinne which they are loath to forgoe? But, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>loued, marke here I beſeech you, the policie of our ghoſtly enemie. Sathan will ſeeme to be (forſooth) very reaſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nable in this point, he ſaith to the ſin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner, Giue thy heart to God, ſerue him, leaue me but one part, one little corner in this houſe, and it ſhall ſuffice me. O dearly beloued, this is but one of Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thans old tricks, hearken not vnto him, heknoweth wel, that if he hath any part, God will haue none, God will haue all or none, God will not hold any part
<pb n="65" facs="tcp:11726:37"/>with Sathan. He will be <hi>ant Caſar, aut nihil,</hi> raigne in thy hart, or haue no part, haue the whole, or let the diuel take al. <hi>My ſonne giue me thine heart</hi> (ſaith God) <hi>Pro.</hi> 23. Learne here (brother) to pluck vp the euill ſeede by the roote, leaue no roote behind of euill cuſtome, leaſt it ſpring vp to the peſtilent weede of a ſetled habite of ſinne, and ſo this vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cleane ſpirit looking into the doore of this ſpirituall houſe, ſeeing it lightly ſwept ouer, <hi>perfunctoriê &amp; velut aliud a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gens,</hi> the filth of euill cuſtomes, ſtill cleauing faſt. This ſweeping well plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeth him, and being inuited hereby, he preſumeth to make a reentrie into this houſe. Let vs therefore (brethren) vſe violence to our wicked cuſtomes, this requireth no light care, old diſeaſes are not ſo lightly cured: <hi>Non leuiore manu, ferroſanantur &amp; igni.</hi> And this let vs doe by oppoſing the cuſtome of ver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tue, and practiſe of godlineſſe againſt our former wicked cuſtoms, that wee may ſtoppe the doore of our ſoules a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt this vncleane ſpirit.</p>
               <p>Thus the vncleane ſpirit ſeeing his
<pb n="66" facs="tcp:11726:38"/>houſe ſwept fit for his purpoſe, looketh further into it, and findeth it alſo emp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie, that is voide of faith, good workes, holy meditations, Chriſtian exerciſes, idle, careleſſe, ſecure, and ſlouthfull in ſeruing of God, neglecting to keepe di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligent watch ouer their ſoules. So the Cittie <hi>Laiſhe,</hi> beeing careleſſe and without miſtruſt, was taken by the children of <hi>Dan, Iudg.</hi> 18 They are not eaſily taken in the ſnare of the diuell, which are intent to any godly exerciſe. We may ſee many whom a man would thinke to bee very much buſied, they are troubled about many things, they are clogged with many cares, ſo that they haue ſearce leyſure <hi>Caput ſcalpere,</hi> to ſcratch their head (as it is in the pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerb) but if we looke into their acti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, we ſhall finde indeede all this buſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes to be but meere idlenes, it is but an idle care which maketh not for the life eternal, or profiteth not the ſoule. Whe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> we ſee children buſied in making hou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes with chippes and ſticks, we iudge them to be idle, but they thinke them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelues to be verie buſie, ſo when we are
<pb n="67" facs="tcp:11726:38"/>plodding and intent to the fading, vaine and momentanie things of the world, neuer fixing our thoughts on the eternall and heauenly things, we may rightly be ſaid to be idle. The true buſines indeede is to be occupied in the ſeruice of the Lord, in prayer, hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring the word, and to keepe carefull watch ouer our ſoule, that the diuell may not finde vs idle. In this life we ſhould be diligent and caſt of all ſlug<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>giſhnes, vntill the wiſhed Sabbath of e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ternall glorie come, when we ſhall la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bour no more, but enioy for euer the fruits of our labours. <hi>Semper aliquid agi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to, vt te diabolus occupatum inueniat: no<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cilê capitur qui bono vacat e<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>e<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> citio,</hi> ſaith <hi>Hiero.</hi> be alwayes doing ſomewhat that the diuell may find thee occupied, hee is not eaſily caught of the diuell, which is buſie in ſome godly exerciſe. Thus when the vnclean ſpirit ſeeth the houſe of thy ſoule emptie, he thinketh it pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pared for him, and maketh no doubt to enter againe into it.</p>
               <p n="3">3 He findeth it alſo garniſhed, euen as a houſe which is adorned, deaked, and
<pb n="68" facs="tcp:11726:39"/>garniſhed, ſeemeth to prouoke and in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uite gueſts to come into it: ſo hee that remoueth not the occaſions of ſinne, doth as it were inuite ſinne to dwell with him. It is needfull therefore, that we doe not onely expell ſinne, but a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uoyde all occaſions of ſinne; <hi>Occaſio fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cit furem</hi> ſaith the old prouerbe, oppor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tunitie and occaſion maketh a thiefe. Much ſurely occaſion auaileth both to vertue and vice; the force whereof is ſuch ſaith <hi>Cicero, vi plerumque ex volup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tate triſtitiam, ex damno lucrum, ex honeſto in honeſtum parturiat: &amp; contrà: breuiter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>que rerum naturam permutat,</hi> that of plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure paine, of loſſe gaine, and of what is honeſt it bringeth forth diſhoneſtie, &amp; ſhortly altereth the nature of things. If thou haſt expelled the ſinne of whore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome &amp; caſt it out, caſt out alſo all oc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>caſions of whoredome with it, as wan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ton companie, alluring harlots, filthy and vnchaſt talking, &amp;c: which are the occaſions of ſinne, and <hi>daemonis ſupellex</hi> ſaith one. If thou haſt forſaken the damnable cuſtome of ſwearing, aban<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>don alſo the ſocietie of prophane
<pb n="69" facs="tcp:11726:39"/>ſwearers, and ſo of all other ſinnes. Occaſions of euill are the Diuels baits, &amp; hookes which he ſaith to catch thee, and to bring thee againe into his ſeruitude. <hi>Si ferreus ſis, ante ignê conſiſtens aliquando diſſolueris: proximus periculo diu tutus no<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> eris.</hi> If thou waſt as hard as iron, the fire will at length diſſolue thee: be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing ſo neare a neighbour to daunger, thou ſhalt not long be ſafe. Familiaritie <hi>ſaepe peccandi occaſione<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> dedit,</hi> giueth occa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion of ſinne: <hi>Iſido. lib.</hi> 2. <hi>ſolilo.</hi> therefore the <hi>Apostle,</hi> 1. <hi>Theſ.</hi> 5. willeth not one<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly to abſtaine from euill, but alſo from all appearance of euill. Take heed of all occaſions of euill, giue no vantage to the enemie, truſt not vnto thine owne ſtrength, <hi>caſt out the bond-woman with her ſonne, Gen.</hi> 21. <hi>Gal.</hi> 4. For if thou caſt out ſinne, &amp; neglect to ſhun the occaſions of ſinne, <hi>Pignus apud daemonem relinquis,</hi> it is as a pledge left in the diuels hands, which, he aſſureth himſelfe thou wilt returne backe againe to fetch: and then he will ſurely hold thee captiue. As <hi>Pharaoh,</hi> bad the <hi>Iſraelite</hi> depart to ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crifice vnto their God, but their cattell
<pb n="70" facs="tcp:11726:40"/>only they ſhould leaue behind: ſo ſaith this helliſh <hi>Pharaoh,</hi> goe (if you will needes) ſacrifice vnto God, that is re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pent you of your ſinne, but onely oc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>caſions of ſinne leaue ſtill with me as a pledge, leaue behind the relikes of your euill cuſtomes, the remembrance of your former delights, &amp;c. Sathan little careth for the reſt. Theſe are the wayes whereby hee reentreth into the houſe from whence he came. &amp;c. Therefore we ſhould pray with the Prophet. <hi>Pſal.</hi> 119. <hi>verſ.</hi> 29. <hi>Viam iniquitatis- amoue à me:</hi> Take from mee the way of iniqui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie, or as the Hebrew worde <hi>(Seker)</hi> ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther importeth of lying: where S. <hi>Am<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>broſe Ser.</hi> 4. <hi>in Pſa. Beati immaculati,</hi> well obſerueth: hee ſaith not, take iniquitie from me, <hi>ſed viam iniquitatis,</hi> the way of iniquitie. The Prophet prayeth that not onely iniquitie may be taken from him, but alſo the occaſion that leadeth vnto iniquitie. <hi>Occaſio enimiter eſt quod ducit ad peccatum:</hi> Occaſion is the way that leadeth vnto ſinne.</p>
               <p>To conclude. The diuell ſeeing the houſe of our ſoule thus ſweeped, emp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie,
<pb n="71" facs="tcp:11726:40"/>and garniſhed (as I ſaid) that is, diſpo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed and prepared for him, hee is inuited hereby to enter againe into the ſame. Then hee goeth and taketh vnto him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe ſeuen other ſpirits worſe then him ſelfe, &amp;c. O fearefull eſtate, which if there be in vs any feeling, if wee haue not a dead conſcience, if we bee not al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>together giuen ouer to a reprobate ſence, is ſufficient to breed in vs an hatred of ſinne, and chiefly to take heed of a relapſe into ſinne, after wee haue eſcaped out of the ſnares of the diuell, let vs neuer be ſecure, but cleaue con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtantly vnto the Lord: for if the diuell enter againe, he will bee more ſtrong, more vigilant to hold faſt his poſſeſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on. He now bandeth himſelfe, he nowe fortifieth his Caſtell, that he bee not a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gaine caſt out. And euen as the knights of <hi>Malta,</hi> after they were ſtrictly beſie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ged by the armie of the great-Turke <hi>Soliman,</hi> and brought into extreame danger, did diligently fortifie their walles, erect ſtrong forts, and furniſh the ſame with all warlike prouiſion, leſt they ſhould fall againe into the like pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rill
<pb n="72" facs="tcp:11726:41"/>which they had eſcaped: ſo this vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cleane ſpirit after he hath againe reco<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uered the fort of mans heart, which be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore hee had loſt, and from which a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt his will he was repelled, is nowe verie warie, that he bee not againe dri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen forth, and therefore by all meanes poſſible hee laboureth to fortifie his houſe, with all his ſpirituall muni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments. And ſo with his infernall bande he entereth in, and dwelleth there.</p>
               <p>But (perhaps) it may bee here asked after what manner the diuell is ſaide to dwell in the wicked. This the Apoſtle <hi>Epheſ.</hi> 2. briefly ſheweth, when he ſaith, that this vncleane ſpirit worketh in the children of diſobedience. He dwelleth therfore by working in them: but what doth he worke? The Philoſopher ſaith: <hi>Omne agens ſibi ſimile agere:</hi> euerie agent worketh like it ſelfe. He laboureth ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore to make a man like himſelfe, that is, proud<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>, cruell, a liar, falſe, enuious, vncleane, an inuenter of euill, deceitful, a man of blood, yea a very diuell in his life &amp; conuerſation. But thou wilt aske, againe, how doth he worke this? It is
<pb n="71" facs="tcp:11726:41"/>certaine, that the diuell cannot com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pell, nor enforce any to wickedneſſe, yet he is able diuerſly to affect the in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feriour powers of the ſoule, and chiefe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly the fantaſie; that hee may ſtirre vp the affections and deſire to euill; he i<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitateth the art of a skilfull painter, which deliniateth all things, that hee painteth ſome times in this faſhion, ſometimes in that, not according to the nature of things, but as it beſt plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeth his fancie: <hi>pictoribus atque poetis, quidlibet audendi ſemper fuit aequa poteſtas.</hi> Poets and Painters, chalenge a Licence to faine. By this art if he would allure thee with the loue of any thing, he ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iecteth it vnto thine eyes, moſt faire, and amiable, when it is nothing leſſe. If he would haue thee hate any thing, he repreſenteth it vnto thee, moſt exe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crable and loathſome. How faire doth he paint golde to the eyes of the co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uetous man, honour to the proude man, reuenge to the wrathfull man, le<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cherie to the looſe man? O how hard and cragged doth he make the way of vertue, and of repentance to the impe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nitent
<pb n="74" facs="tcp:11726:42"/>ſinner? yea the very ſame thing he exhibiteth to thy minde, ſometime faire and ſometime deformed at his pleaſure, as beſt hee thinketh it may ſerue to worke our deſtruction.</p>
               <p>Thou happelie wilt replie that thou neuer didſt feele this his working in thy ſelfe. This is, becauſe thou neuer didſt reſiſt him, thou neuer didſt with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtand his temptations, thou yeeldeſt vnto thy deſire, thou neuer didſt ſtriue to come out of his ſnares. We ſee a birde that is caught in the ſnare, as long as he ſtandeth ſtill, is delighted and feedeth vpon the baite, he findeth not the force of the ſnare: but when hee aſſaileth to flye away, then he feeleth the ſtrength of the ginne, with which he is holden faſt, which before he per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiued not. So whoſoeuer boileth with inteſtiue hatred towards his neighbor, or with the deſire of reuenge, or with the furie of fornication, or with the delight of wrongfull gotten good, or with vnchaſt loue, or is caught in a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nie other ſnare of the diuell: let him but beginne to come out of theſe
<pb n="75" facs="tcp:11726:42"/>ſnares, and to breake theſe bands of ſathan, or to ſubdue his long continu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed cuſtomes of any vice, and then ſhall he proue the ſtrength and power of this enemie. <hi>Eos pulſare negligit quot quieto iure posſidere ſe ſentit. Greg.</hi> He let<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teth them alone whome he keepeth vnder quiet poſſeſſion.</p>
               <p>So the laſt ſtate of that man is worſe then the firſt. Here our Sauiour teach<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth how dangerous it is to make a re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lapſe into ſinne, we are deliuered from the power of darkneſſe, and ſathan in Baptiſine, we are taken out of the bands, and chaines of ignorance and errour, through knowledge of the truth, for it is that which maketh vs free, <hi>Io.</hi> 8. Farre be it from vs (brethren) that either through hatred of the truth in Doctrine, or through impietie in life and manners, we ſhould againe ſubmit our necke to the diuels yoake. For e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen as in bodily diſeaſes, when the ſicke hath recouered his former health if afterward through his owne default, he falleth againe into the ſame mala<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>die, his ſicknes is more grieuous and
<pb n="76" facs="tcp:11726:43"/>dangerous' then at the firſt, becauſe na<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ture now is decayed and weakened: ſo after by the grace of God, and the preaching of his word we haue eſcaped out of the ſnares of the diuell, if we fall againe into the ſame ſinne, our eſtate ſhall be more perillous then at firſt. Sinne in his firſt and beſt eſtate is an cuill, verie hurtfull and dangerous, the malice whereof we cannot better be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hold, then by his contraries, for <hi>rectum est iudex ſui obliqui:</hi> The ſtraight is the beſt tryer of the crooked. <hi>Omne bonum</hi> (ſaith the Philoſopher) <hi>continet vel ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nestum, vel vtile, vet incundum:</hi> Euerie good conteineth in it, either what is honeſt; profitable, or pleaſant. Where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore vertue is <hi>magnum bonum,</hi> a great good, becauſe it containeth in it what<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoeuer is honeſt, profitable, or pleaſant. God is <hi>ſummum bonum,</hi> the ſoueraigne good, becauſe he is <hi>ſummè vtilis, ſummè honestus, &amp; ſummè delectabilis.</hi> Which 2 in a moſt perfect manner are in God. Whereby we may conclude, that ſee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing ſinne ſeparateth a man from theſe 3. kinds of good, it followeth it muſt
<pb n="77" facs="tcp:11726:43"/>needs be a pernicious and execrable e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uill, becauſe it maketh vs which were created to be capable of the <hi>ſummum bonum,</hi> to be altogether vnapt for the ſame. 1. Sinne is oppoſed to the profi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>table good, becauſe it bringeth infinite damage and loſſe vnto the ſinner, for it expelleth God the ſoueraigne good, from his habitation of our ſoules. Not as a more ſtronger driueth out the weaker: but when through vices and our filthy life we diſhonour God, then is God ſayd to be caſt out of our hearts. For as men are wont co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>monly to ſay: I will not thruſt thee out, but I will ſo vſe thee, that thou ſhalt haue litle plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure to ſtay with me. So whe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> God ſeeth that we more eſteeme the dung, husks, and traſh of this world, then we doe him, he forſaketh his dwelling and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>parteth, being ſo iniuriouſly vſed. To vſe this familiar example: If thou be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing maried to a beautifull, honeſt, and louing wife, deſcended of honourable parentage, ſhouldeſt fixe thy loue vpon a fowle, deformed, and filthy <hi>Neger,</hi> place her by thee at the higher end of
<pb n="78" facs="tcp:11726:44"/>the table, compell thy wife to ſerue her as a vile handmaide; may ſhe not iuſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly complaine of thee, and willingly forſake thy companie? In like manner, when we eſteeme more our owne luſts and appetites, &amp; preferre them before the loue of God, following whore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome, enuie, malice, blaſphemies, op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſion, &amp;c. Should God take any de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>light to dwell in our hearts? and when God departeth from vs, it is the moſt greeuous, and incomparable euill, that poſſible may happen vnto vs, and greateſt loſt that may be imagined. For as we ſee many to inſult vpon the Wi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dowes and fatherleſſe, becauſe for the moſt part they are deſtitute of friends, to ſuccour and defend their cauſe, and therefore expoſed to all iniurie and oppreſſion: ſo the ſoule that is deſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tute of Gods aide and protection lyeth naked, and open to the malice and fury of the vncleane ſpirit. This, <hi>Dauids</hi> e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nemies well knew when they ſayd, <hi>Pſa.</hi> 71. <hi>God hath forſaken him, let vs perſecat<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> and take him, for there is none to deliuer him.</hi> And therefore this princely Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phet,
<pb n="79" facs="tcp:11726:44"/>wiſely prayed, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 51. <hi>Caſt me not away from thy preſence, and take not thy ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly ſpirit from me.</hi> For euen as when the court remoueth, all the attendants and courteors departe alſo: ſo when God departeth from the ſoule, all bleſſings, goodneſſe and graces goe away with him. O conſider this, yee that forget God, and with a feeling heart conſider now, whether there be any thing ſo vnprofitable to man as is ſinne, which depriueth him of the fountaine of all goodneſſe, and ouerwhelmeth him with ſuch a deluge of cuils? O (my brethren) is it not to be wondred at that any reaſonable creature, knowing this (as reaſon it ſelfe teacheth vs) ſhould be ſo eaſily drawne by the ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mie of mankind, to commit (and that without any remorſe of conſcience) all wickednes, and vncleaneſſe? O then let vs take heede and be carefully care<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full how we fall from God, for if we de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>part from the mildneſſe of his mercie, we muſt of neceſſitie fall into the rigor of his iuſtice. Euen as a trauailer, the farther he goeth from the Eaſt, the
<pb n="80" facs="tcp:11726:45"/>nearer hee approacheth to the Weſt, and the farther hee goeth from the South, the nearer he commeth to the North: ſo the ſinner, the farther he de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>parteth from Gods mercy, the ſooner hee falleth into the hands of Gods iuſtice.</p>
               <p n="2">2 Sinne is alſo oppoſite to honeſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie, and therefore a vile, vnhoneſt, and ſhamefull euill. For it alwayes brandeth the ſinner with a note of infamie, which is the cauſe that the wicked doer hi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deth himſelfe, and would be ſeene of none, for he knoweth if his euill deeds be eſpied, he hath loſt his honeſt repu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tation, and credite among good men, and with ſhame and ignomine is poin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted at of all men. <hi>Qui malè agit edit lu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cem, he that euill doth hateth the light, Io.</hi> 3. <hi>verſ.</hi> 20.</p>
               <p n="3">3 It is oppoſed <hi>bono delectabil<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>,</hi> to the pleaſant and delightſome good: and therefore it is an euill full of ſad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe, greefe, and vexation of minde, and bringeth not only eternall death, but alſo maketh this preſent life bitter and vnpleaſant: for God will not ſuffer
<pb n="81" facs="tcp:11726:45"/>ſinne to eſcape his vengeance, it hath euer Gods reuenging hand following it. Knowe (therefore) <hi>and behold, that it is an euill and a bitter thing, that thou haſt forſaken the Lord thy God, Iere.</hi> 2. <hi>verſ.</hi> 19. I will not heere ſpeake of the eternall puniſhme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t, which ſhall torme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t the wic<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ked, but of the horror &amp; ſecret ſtripes, wherewith their conſcience in this life tormenteth them. Sinne hath euer an euill end, and leaueth behind it cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taine ſtinges and prickes, which are ſtil whipping wicked men, and drawing them to deſperation. It is like poyſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nedwine, the force whereof is found in the end. Sinne is like a ſtrong wine, which inebriateth a man, and berea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ueth him of his ſences, ſo that he may be compared vnto a brute beaſt, <hi>Pſa.</hi> 40.12. It layeth before the eyes, a falſe co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lour and ſhewe of pleaſure, as honour, riches, worldly delight, &amp;c. But when ſinne is accompliſhed, it leaueth a kind of bitterneſſe, which will not ſuffer the heart to bee at reſt, and the repining conſcience is inwardly gnawing &amp; bi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting. And euen as <hi>Iob.</hi> 1. in the midſt
<pb n="82" facs="tcp:11726:46"/>of his calamities, neuer wanted a meſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſenger which brought him euill newes: ſo his <hi>Alaſtor</hi> is neuer wanting to the wicked, after the accompliſhment of ſinne, which layeth before his eyes, the good he hath loſt when he offen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deth God, and the wretched eſtate in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to which he is fallen: and euill conſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence is an odious companion, a turbu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lent tempeſt, a ſcourge which inwardly whippeth the wicked, and counterpoy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zeth their pleaſures with bitter Aloes, and ſtill caſteth <hi>Colloquintida</hi> into their ſauces, and ſcarſe is the garlicke of <hi>Ae<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gypt</hi> taſted, but it bringeth teares from the eyes. So that this of <hi>Eliphas</hi> is true, <hi>Iob.</hi> 25.<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>2. <hi>The wicked man is continually as one that trauaileth with child, a ſound of feare in his eares, &amp;c.</hi> O the greeuous and intollerable yoake of ſathan: O the ſlauiſh condition of the ſeruants of ſinne, with how great labour doe the wicked ſeeke the things they deſire, with what feare doe they poſſeſſe them? with what ſorrowe doe they loſe them? as they that worſhip the beaſt, ſhall haue no reſt day nor night, <hi>Apo.</hi>
                  <pb n="83" facs="tcp:11726:46"/>14. No more ſhall they which adore their beaſtly appetites. Sinne it ſelfe is a greeuous torment, and puniſhment of the ſinner, as the light of nature tolde <hi>Seneca,</hi> when he ſaide, <hi>ſceleris in ſcelere ſupplicium eſt.</hi> The puniſhment of ſinne, is in ſinne. All things to a wicked man are ſeaſoned with gall &amp; worme<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wood: if they be in proſperitie, they are vexed with continuall feare of loo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing their felicitie, if they be in aduer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſitie, in what care and ſorrowe doe they liue which neuer ſuffereth them to be at reſt. O the vnhappie, and wretched life, that is a ſeruant of ſinne, and a ſlaue to his owne luſts. But marke nowe the importunitie of ſinne: If a wicked man be litle iniured of any, ſee how mad and diſcontented in minde he getteth him home, he abſtaineth from meate and drinke, he cannot ſleepe nor take reſt, hee armeth himſelfe and ſeeketh to reuenge him. How much more plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure, ioy, and tranquillitie of minde doe the ſeruants of God inioy, which hauing receaued many iniuries, are not moued to wrath, they breake not their
<pb n="84" facs="tcp:11726:47"/>ſleepe, they are ioyfull, they ſeeke not reuenge, they giue place vnto wrath, they commit their cauſe into Gods hands, who hath ſaide, <hi>Vengeance is mine, and I will repay, Rom.</hi> 12. For as the diuell and the world, miſerably afflic<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teth their followers in this life: ſo Chriſt giueth perfect peace, ioy, and true delights, vnto ſuch as faithfully ſerue him. The diuell commandeth to take reuenge, God willeth to forgiue: tell me now which is moſt painfull, ei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther to forgiue or to ſeeke vengeance? Aske the whoremonger in the midſt of the ſurie of his fornication, (who profuſeth his wealth, vndertaketh many labours, ſpendeth many wake<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full nights, with infamie &amp; the detri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of his good name, with the loſſe ſometime of his life, and without Gods great mercie of his ſoule alſo for euer, and all to ſerue his filthy luſt) whether there be not greater paine and labour, in ſeruing vnchaſt loue, then in lea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding an honeſt, and chaſt life?</p>
               <p>Now (brethren) ſeeing that ſinne is ſo vnprofitable, ſo hurtfull, ſo diſho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſt,
<pb n="85" facs="tcp:11726:47"/>and ſo full of ſorrowe, labour, and griefe, which make a moſt trouble<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſome life Let vs (I beſeech you) learne hereby to fly from ſinne as from a ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pent, hate it as a deadly poyſon, ſhunne the occaſions thereof, as a contagious peſtilence: and if at any time through humane frailtie we fall into ſinne, let vs linger no delayes, but preſently ſtriue <hi>by amendment of life, to come out of the ſnares of the diuell.</hi> 2. <hi>Tim.</hi> 2.26. And ſtu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy euer to intertain the feare of God in our hearts, and nouriſh the ſame by de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uout prayer, hearing of the word, holy meditations, &amp;c.</p>
               <p>Heere we haue ſeene how euill the ſtate of ſinne is, but the laſt ſtate of that man (ſaith Chriſt) is worſe then the firſt, 1. in reſpect of the diuell; 2 in regarde of the ſinner himſelfe; and 3. in reſpect of God: 1. in regarde of the diuell, becauſe now he handleth them more cruellie, whom he hath caught againe, and more vigilantly watcheth and obſerueth them then before. Euen as a man that is detained in priſon, his keeper ſeeing him to be an honeſt man
<pb n="86" facs="tcp:11726:48"/>and of noble birth, doth not ſo ſtrictly keepe him, nor ſo ſtrongly fetter him, as he doth others, whom he miſtruſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teth: but if he breaketh priſon and eſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>capeth, if againe he be taken, his kee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per now looketh more narrowly vnto him, putteth on him ſtrong yrons, watcheth him night and day, leaſt hee ſhould practiſe againe to flie. The like doth this helliſh Iaylor, when the ſin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner his captiue, hath by the grace of God, eſcaped out of his priſon, if hee be ſo vnhappie, as through careleſſe ſecuritie, to come againe vnder the captiuitie of the diuel, his laſt eſtate (O fearefull ſaying) ſhall be worſe then the firſt, hee putteth now heauier chaines vpon him, he more carefully watcheth him, he multiplieth his temptations, he laboureth to ſhut the ſpirituall doores of the ſoule, that godly meditations and diuine inſpirations (if it be poſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble) may enter in. If he ſeeth that fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miliaritie with good men, be an occa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion to keepe thee from him, he dili<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gently beſtirreth him, to withdrawe thee from the ſocietie of godly men,
<pb n="87" facs="tcp:11726:48"/>and entiſeth thee to ſort thy ſelfe with wicked companie. If he perceiue that comming to Sermons, withholdeth thee from him, he indeauoureth to withdrawe thy loue and deſire from comming to Church, or elſe diſtrac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teth thy minde, with a thouſand pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phane thoughts, that the word of God may take no roote in thy heart, <hi>but bee vnto thee, the ſauour of death, vnto death.</hi> 2. <hi>Cor.</hi> 2.16. And this is it our Sauiour ſaith, <hi>he taketh to him</hi> 7. <hi>other ſpirits worſe then himſelfe.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="2">2 It is worſe in regard of the ſinner himſelfe, becauſe through cuſtome of ſinning, he commeth into an habite of ſinne, and ſo the more vnapt to receiue any godly motions, and the more hardly conuerted. As one that for theft, or any other crime hath often<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>times bin caſt into priſon, at length be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>commeth ſhameleſſe impudent, and as the prouerbe is, <hi>perfricuit frontem,</hi> hee hath wiped away all ſhame, and cannot bluſh, ſo indurate is he in his wickneſſe; or as a garment that with continuall vſe is worne ſo thinne, that it will not
<pb n="88" facs="tcp:11726:49"/>hold the mending: ſo many haue ſo weakened, and worne their ſpirituall powers, with long cuſtome of ſinning, that neither Diuine inſpirations, nor the admonition of the Preachers may faſten on them any ſpirituall plaiſter, to cure and amende the ruptures of their ſoules. <hi>Valerius</hi> ſaith, that the <hi>Cre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tians,</hi> when they bitterly curſed them whom they hated, were wont to vſe this forme of execration, <hi>vt mala conſuetu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dine delectentur:</hi> that they might be de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lighted with ſome wicked cuſtome. This ſeemed but a modeſt kind of curſe, <hi>ſed eſſicaciſſimum vltionis euentum reperiunt.</hi> But the euent proueth it an effectuall kind of reuenge, ſaith he. <hi>lib.</hi> 7. <hi>cap.</hi> 2. We ſee a candle or a firebrand but now put out, will quickly reſume light againe with the leaſt touch of the fire, but if it hath bin long extinct, it is not ſo ſoone kindled: ſo the ſoule that falleth into ſinne; if ſtraight it taketh hold of repentance, it is more eaſily conuerted, and reſumeth againe the light of grace; but after it falleth often into the ſame ſinne, and through cu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtome
<pb n="89" facs="tcp:11726:49"/>is inueterate in wickedneſſe, and hath quite loſt the heate of deuotion, is hardly reſtored to his former eſtate. Conſider brethren I beſeech you, if a woman that hath a long time bin de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tained in priſon, ſhould there haue a childe, the childe being yet young though in a ſtrict, filthy and ſtincking priſon, playeth, reioyceth, and is mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry: becauſe hee neuer knewe what li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bertie is, nor euer proued any other kind of life, but the mother with a hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uie heart ſaith: O my childe, if thou knoweſt our miſerie, and hadeſt tryed my former libertie and ſelicitie: thou wouldeſt not reioyce, but with teares bewaile our wretched eſtate. O ſinfull man and woman, which art faſt tied with the fetters and chaines of vices, and yet in this ſtraight priſon of ſathan doſt reioyce, as if all things went well with thee. And what is the cauſe here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of? ſurely becauſe long cuſtome of ſinne, hath now conuerted it in <hi>alteram naturam,</hi> into another nature, which maketh thee forget the heauenly good things, and lookeſt only into the pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent
<pb n="90" facs="tcp:11726:50"/>and momentanie pleaſures O that thou didſt conſider what, &amp; how great the things are which are promiſed vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to vs in heauen, ſurely al earthly things would then ſeeme vile vnto thee, for all earthly ſubſtance without god<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lineſſe is death not life, captiuitie not libertie, darkneſſe not light. <hi>Prauus vſus vix aboletur, asſidua conſuetudo viti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>um in naturam conuertit, Aug. in ſolilo.</hi> A wicked vſe is hardly aboliſhed, a con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinuall cuſtome conuerteth vice into nature. <hi>Quo ſit imbuta recens ſeruabit o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dorem teſta diu.</hi> Saith the Poet. <hi>Horace in Epiſt. ad Lol.</hi>
               </p>
               <q>
                  <l>The Pitcher long wil hold the taſt,</l>
                  <l>Of that which first was in it caſt.</l>
               </q>
               <p>It is reported of <hi>Alexander</hi> the great that mightie conqueror of the world, that albeit in his manners, and gate in going, he reſembled his Schoolemaiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter <hi>Leonides,</hi> yet he euer taſted of the vices, with which at firſt he was ſeaſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned. Wherefore (brethren) I exhort you for our Lord Ieſus Chriſts ſake,
<pb n="91" facs="tcp:11726:50"/>who ſhed his precious bloud for vs, that ye will diligently take heede of e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uill cuſtomes, leaſt your hearts be har<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dened in ſinne, and ſo ſinne growe into an habite, but without delay caſt of your olde ſinnefull conuerſation, and be renued in the ſpirit of your mindes, and betime put on the new man, which after God, is created in righte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſneſſe, and true holineſſe, <hi>Ephe.</hi> 4.23. O conſider, that in thy firſt eſtate thou dideſt fight againſt the fleſh, the world and the diuell: but if thou ſtill addeſt ſinne vpon ſinne, thou prouokeſt be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſides theſe another enemie, wicked cuſtome, which will wage hoſtile warre againſt thee, drawe thee after it, and will bring thee into that wretched eſtate, that thou ſhalt not feele the ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lice of ſinne, but drinke in iniquitie like wine, and ſo be the more hardly con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerted. Let vs flie all occaſions, auoyde the ſocietie of wicked men, the lillie is hardly preſerued vnhurte among thoſe thornes. And ſo in this a reſpect, the laſt ſtate of ſinne is worſe then the firſt.</p>
               <p n="3">
                  <pb n="92" facs="tcp:11726:51"/> 3 Thirdly, the laſt ſtate of ſinne is worſe then the firſt, in reſpect of God: becauſe the farther the ſinner depar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teth from God, the oftner he <hi>returneth like the dogge to his owne vomite, and as the Sow that was waſhed to her wallowing in the mire.</hi> 
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>. <hi>Pet.</hi> 2.22. The more God departeth from him, and giueth <hi>them vp to their harts luſt, to a reprobate minde, vnto vile affections. Rom.</hi> 1 <hi>verſ.</hi> 24.28. As the phyſition giueth ouer the ſicke, which through his intemperancie and diſordered life, falleth many times in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to a relapſe of ſickenes. Wherefore the Lord complaineth againſt <hi>Babel, Ier.</hi> 51. <hi>We would haue cured Babel, but ſhe could not be healed, forſake her, &amp;c.</hi> And euen as a trauailer, the more he goeth on his way, the farther he is from the place from whence hee came: ſo the greater ſinne and more often, that a man committeth, the farther is he ſtill from God. But marke heere the poli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cie of Sathan: when hee cannot drawe a man (eſpecially ſuch as haue bin ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>erciſed in godlineſſe) at one pull from God, he laboureth to effect this <hi>pede<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tentim
<pb n="93" facs="tcp:11726:51"/>&amp; paulatim,</hi> by little and litle: e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen as feuers and other infirmities of the bodie, are the forerunners of death: ſo many infirmities of the ſoule, goe before the committing of many ſinnes in action. Thou commeſt deuoutly daily to prayer: by litle and litle, thou groweſt more colde, at laſt thou waxeſt keycolde, and vtterly neglecteſt the dutie of prayer. Thou repayreſt zea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>louſly to neare the word preached hee it be euery day in the weeke, at laſt thy zeale waxeth more colde, &amp; then thou ſaiſt it is ſufficient to heare a Sermon vpon the Sabboth day: in the end thou ſayeſt to what purpoſe is ſo much prea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ching, and ſo by litle and litle, ſathan draweth thee to deſpiſe Preachers, and contemne the word of God, and by de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>grees bringeth thee to vtter deſtructi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on. So our Mother <hi>Eue,</hi> by litle and li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tle fell from God, firſt ſhe beheld the Tree in the midſt of the Garden, that it was a faire Tree, and pleaſant to the eie, then ſhe deſired the fruite, next, ſhe plucked it and did eate, <hi>and ſo tranſgreſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed Gods commandement. Gen.</hi> 3.6. So
<pb n="94" facs="tcp:11726:52"/>
                  <hi>Caine</hi> from a litle enuie, which at firſt might eaſily haue bin ſuppreſſed, gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uing place to the diuell, his hatred ſo increaſed that it grewe at laſt to mur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther. Take heede therefore, <hi>principiis ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſta</hi> reſiſt betime, <hi>lubricus eſt ſerpens anti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quus,</hi> whoſe firſt ſuggeſtions, if they be not reſiſted <hi>totus in intima cordis dum non ſentitur, illabitur. Iſidor.</hi> The diuell is a ſlipperie ſerpent, whoſe head, that is, his firſt ſuggeſtions, if they be not re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiſted, he windeth in his whole bodie, ere thou be aware. And that he may the ſooner withdrawe vs from God, he laboureth firſt to corrupt and falſifie the election of our will, which one cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leth <hi>amoris &amp; affectionum bilancem</hi> the ballance of our loue and affections: whereby it commeth to paſſe, that in the eſtimate of our loue, we ſo litle eſteeme God, and the heauenly good things: that in our election we preferre the creature before the creator, and tranſitorie things before the heauenly. So the Iewes, Chriſt and <hi>Barrabas,</hi> be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing put in this deceitfull ballance, in their choiſe <hi>Barrabas</hi> waighed downe
<pb n="95" facs="tcp:11726:52"/>Chriſt. <hi>Math.</hi> 27. Becauſe they more eſteemed <hi>Barrabas</hi> then Chriſt. Thou wilt ſay, that the Iewes deſerued eter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nall torments for that they ſo vniuſtly did ponderate the different worthynes of theſe 2. But if one ſhould demaunde of thee, whether thou loueſt Chriſt or <hi>Barrabas?</hi> no doubt thou wouldeſt ſay Chriſt: but if thou makeſt choiſe of one worſe then <hi>Barrabas,</hi> what wilt thou ſay? what if thou more eſteemeſt ſinne then Chriſt? thou takeſt from thy neighbour his ſubſtance, thou be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trayeſt thy ſoule vnto the diuell, thou wilt ſweare, and forſweare, to increaſe thy wealth, and for the gaining of one groate, thou forſakeſt Chriſt, doſt thou not now more eſteeme thy gaine then God? Doſt thou not loue ſinne, and the diuell more then Chriſt? and ſeeing the diuell is worſe then <hi>Barrabas,</hi> and thou loueſt the diuel more then Chriſt, it neceſſarily followeth, that thou art worſe then the Iewes. And what is the cauſe hereof, but the ballance of loue or hatred, which is placed in thy will, which ſathan adulterateth, and falſifi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth
<pb n="96" facs="tcp:11726:53"/>in the eſtimate of this loue, and in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clineth it to the worſt? And ſo as the ſinner through the malice of his will, turneth away from God: ſo God tur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neth his face from him, which is the greateſt of all euils. And euen as the farther one goeth from the Sunne, the longer is his ſhadowe, (for in the eue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning the Sunne declining, euerie thing hath the greater ſhadowe) ſo the far<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther a man departeth from God, the greater ſhadowes of worldly vanities followe him: for what are all earthly things, which ſo greedily we deſire but ſhadowes? as the wicked themſelues (but too late) ſhall confeſſe: <hi>Wiſd. 5. All thoſe things are paſſed away as a ſhadow.</hi> And the farther we plunge our ſelues in the loue of the world, the farther ſtil we are from God, and therefore the more difficill our conuerſion. And e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen as the Sunne, the farther it depar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teth from any Countrie, the more colde and barraine it maketh it: con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trariwiſe, the nearer the Sunne direc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teth his courſe to any region, the more warme and fruitfull it is, and the ſooner
<pb n="97" facs="tcp:11726:53"/>it bringeth forth fruite: ſo the nearer our Lord Ieſus Chriſt, the Sonne of righteouſneſſe is vnto vs, and with his preſence and ho<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>e beames of his grace &amp; holy ſpirit, colluſtrateth our ſoules, the ſooner and more aboundantly we fructifie, be conuerted, bring forth the fruits of pietie, to the ioyfull and bleſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed harueſt of eternall life. But when Chriſt the true Sonne of righteouſneſſe departeth, hee leaueth the ſoule deſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>late, barraine, vnfruitfull, and openeth the gate vnto all vices. And therefore the Lord ſaith by his Prophet, <hi>Hoſe.</hi> 9.1<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>. <hi>Woe be vnto them, when I depart from them.</hi> For as the ſpirit of God dwelling in our hearts maketh the way of vertue eaſie and pleaſant; ſo the abſence of Gods ſpirit, (when through ſinne we greeue the ſpirite of God) maketh the way of repentance, difficill and vnplea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſant. And ſo in this reſpect the laſt ſtate of the ſinner is worſe then the firſt.</p>
               <p>Wherefore (brethren) I beſeech and exhort you, in the bowels of mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cie,
<pb n="98" facs="tcp:11726:54"/>of our Lord Ieſus Chriſt, that yee would euer remember this wholſome caueat of our Sauiour, <hi>Io.</hi> 5.14. <hi>Sinne, no more, least a worſe thing happen unto thee.</hi> Take we heede of often back ly<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding. <hi>Remember Lots wife, Luc.</hi> 17. <hi>Gen.</hi> 19.26. For if we, <hi>after we haue eſcaped from the filthineſſe of the world, through the knowledge of the Lord, and of our Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uiour Ieſus Chriſt,</hi> are yet intangled a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gaine <hi>therin &amp; ouercome, our later end wil be worſe, then the beginning,</hi> 2. <hi>Pet.</hi> 2.20. Let vs take the preſent opportunitie of repentance, let vs not thinke to find it more eaſie heereafter, when all the cau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes of difficultie are increaſed, by ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding ſinne vpon ſinne. When an euill cuſtome hath taken a deepe habite in our hearts, when ſinne by continu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ance, bringeth a plea of preſcription: when the diuell hath more ſtrongly fortified his Caſtle, which is our ſoule, when God which is our light is departed farther from vs, when the powers of our ſoules, become more
<pb n="99" facs="tcp:11726:54"/>weake by receiuing of many wounds, and more inſufficient goodneſſe. To conclude, againe I exhort you (bre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thren) that taking pittie vpon your ſelues, whiles yet this life laſteth, whiles yet there is time for mercie, while the the Iudge himſelfe calleth you to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pentance, louingly expecteth you, offereth his grace, reacheth out his hand to receiue you, before the gate of heauen be ſhut againſt you, that yee would in time prouide for your ſelues: that walking the way of repentance, the hand of the Lord guiding &amp; directing you, yee may come after this earthly Pilgrimage, into the bleſſed <hi>Chanaan</hi> of eternall felicitie, where ſhall be eter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nall health, and healthfull eternitie, where our ioy ſhall neuer decreaſe, nor loue euer waxe colde, euen that bleſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſedneſſe which the eye hath not ſeene, the care hath not heard, neither hath entred into the heart of man, <hi>which God hath prepared for them that loue him.</hi> 1. <hi>Cor.</hi> 2.9. To whome with the Sonne and the holy Ghoſt, 3. perſons in one
<pb facs="tcp:11726:55"/>moſt glorious Trinitie, one God in V<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nitie, might, maieſtie, be all honour, praiſe, power and dominion, now and for euer more, A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men.</p>
               <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
               <pb facs="tcp:11726:55" rendition="simple:additions"/>
               <pb facs="tcp:11726:56" rendition="simple:additions"/>
               <pb facs="tcp:11726:56"/>
            </div>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
